<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of some proceedings of Lt. Col. Iohn Lilburn, and his associates: with some examination, and animadversion upon papers lately printed, and scattered abroad. One called The earnest petition of many free-born people of this Kingdome : another, The mournfull cries of many thousand poor tradesmen, who are ready to famish for want of bread, or The warning tears of the oppressed. Also a letter sent to Kent. Likewise a true relation of Mr. Masterson's minister of Shoreditch, signed with his owne hand. Published by authority, for the undeceiving of those that are misled by these deceivers, in many places of this Kingdom.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82113</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D625</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E427_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204593</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864062</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864062</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116281</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82113)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116281)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 67:E427[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of some proceedings of Lt. Col. Iohn Lilburn, and his associates: with some examination, and animadversion upon papers lately printed, and scattered abroad. One called The earnest petition of many free-born people of this Kingdome : another, The mournfull cries of many thousand poor tradesmen, who are ready to famish for want of bread, or The warning tears of the oppressed. Also a letter sent to Kent. Likewise a true relation of Mr. Masterson's minister of Shoreditch, signed with his owne hand. Published by authority, for the undeceiving of those that are misled by these deceivers, in many places of this Kingdom.</title>
                  <author>Masterson, Geo. (George)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Howard, and are to be sold at his Shop, the Crown and Bible at Budge-Row-End, near Canning-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Domini, M DC XLVIII. [1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 14th", "1647"; the last I in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</term>
               <term>Mournfull cryes of many thousand poore tradesmen.</term>
               <term>To the supream authority of England, the Commons assembled in Parliament. The earnest petition of many free-born people of this nation.</term>
               <term>Levellers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116281:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION Of ſome PROCEEDINGS of L<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Col. Iohn Lilburn, And his ASSOCIATES: WITH Some Examination, and Animadverſion upon Papers lately Printed, and ſcattered abroad. One called <hi>The earneſt Petition of many Free-born People of this Kingdome:</hi> Another, <hi>The mournfull Cries of many thouſand poor Tradeſmen, who are ready to famiſh for want of Bread, Or,</hi> The Warning Tears of the Oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Letter ſent to KENT.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe a true Relation of Mr. <hi>Maſterſon's,</hi> Miniſter of SHOREDITCH, Signed with his owne hand.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authority, for the undeceiving of thoſe that are miſled by theſe Deceivers, in many places of this Kingdom.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 18.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that is firſt in his Cauſe, ſeemeth juſt, but his neighbour commeth and ſearcheth him.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 3.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>But Evill men, and Seducers, ſhall wax worſe and worſe, deceiving, and being deceived.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Harward,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, the Crown and Bible at Budge-Row-End, near Canning-ſtreet. <hi>Anno Domini, MDCXLVIII.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:116281:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116281:2"/>
            <head>A Declaration, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here can be nothing more evident to any that will give themſelves leave <hi>maturely</hi> to weigh and compare the paſt and preſent ſtate of affaires in this Kingdome with an <hi>impartiall</hi> Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than that all the preſſures <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly impoſed,</hi> the <hi>late Warre,</hi> the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſtempers,</hi> and <hi>future threatned danger thereby,</hi> doe all grow out of the ſame <hi>root,</hi> and flow from the ſame <hi>fountaine;</hi> and will lead, if they be purſued, to one and the ſame <hi>end,</hi> Even that which was firſt in the intention of the firſt Deſigners, <hi>The ſetling of Tyranny, and inſlaving the People.</hi> And although he that ſhall look upon theſe things only <hi>en paſſant,</hi> will ſcarce believe that ſuch diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Principles and pretentions as are held out to view, ſhould ſerve the ſame ends. And though it ſhould ſeem there could be nothing at greater diſtance to the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116281:3"/>of ſome, who are abuſed into theſe <hi>diſtempers,</hi> than to <hi>promote ſlavery</hi> and <hi>haſten ruine.</hi> Yet they who are unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed and uningaged in them, and inſtructed in, and convinced of the Grand Deſigne of <hi>thoſe who began our troubles,</hi> and how it is ſtill carryed on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> can both ſee the <hi>Artifice</hi> by which they are raiſed and fomented, and the <hi>End</hi> to which they tend, and where at they are like to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive; There is no need to reckon up what the ſtate of this Kingdom was before the breaking out of theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, being in ſuch condition of wealth, and all mnaner of proſperity, as made it the Subject of Envie to thoſe who knew not what was deſigned againſt it. But no leſſe than an <hi>abſolute Tyranny</hi> would pleaſe the <hi>King,</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the hearts of his people by a <hi>juſt Government,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Lawes, and the Limits of his Truſt, and there by to command their perſons, and purſes, and all; for the good of all, was beneath <hi>Royallity.</hi> And that it was fitter for a King <hi>to take, than ask,</hi> was then <hi>State Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> and the practiſe ſuitable. We were to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delled to a <hi>forreign pattern,</hi> and in purſuance thereof, all manner of Arbitrary exactions, and impoſitions were laid upon the people, the particulars will not be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten this Age, and need not a recapitulation. A <hi>Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> had ſeized the people, and their <hi>uſuall Phyſick</hi> was denyed them; and when twas grown dangerous even to ſigh for a <hi>Parliament,</hi> the Kings neceſſities by the ſtirres in <hi>Scotland</hi> inforce him to call <hi>one.</hi> But that was not the <hi>firſt the King had broken,</hi> and he then knew well enough when it would not <hi>ſerve his turne,</hi> and <hi>verefie Edicts,</hi> How to keep it from <hi>ſerving the people</hi> for the recovery of their <hi>Liberty:</hi> His neceſſities encreaſe, this preſent Parliament is called; and in regard of ſo many broken before, this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116281:3"/>was not able to ſerve the neceſſities of the Kingdome, unleſſe it were put beyond his power to break; And therefore was continued by Law till the Houſes by joynt conſent ſhould diſſolve it; Now the King being faſt, as to uſuall Court Stratagems, hath recourſe to <hi>force,</hi> deales with one <hi>Army,</hi> tempts <hi>another,</hi> fruſtrate in both; impeacheth Members, comes himſelfe to fetch them, nothing takes; He retires into the North, reſolves a <hi>Conqueſt</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>People,</hi> the <hi>Lawes,</hi> and though to blind the ſhort-ſighted multitude, He forbids the repaire of <hi>Papiſts</hi> to the <hi>Court,</hi> yet his principall Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in it are thoſe his <hi>good Subjects;</hi> He ſet up his Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard, raiſeth an Army, maketh Warre againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Kingdome, and put it to the tryall of the Sword, whether he ſhall govern by the <hi>Lawes,</hi> or by his Will <hi>without Law.</hi> In the proſecution of which <hi>appeal</hi> to the Lord of Hoſts, he hath <hi>loſt his Cauſe,</hi> which ſtands determined againſt him by a <hi>full Conqueſt</hi> of all his forces; And thereby an happy opportunity given, not only to deliver from thoſe <hi>late Exactions,</hi> and to make their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne <hi>impoſsible,</hi> but for the recovery and eſtabliſhment of all that <hi>juſt Freedome</hi> that may make a people <hi>happy,</hi> as they ſtand in the <hi>Naturall Conſtitution, and Civill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation,</hi> and <hi>diſtinct and mutuall relations</hi> of the people of <hi>England; if themſelves hinder not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The way of <hi>force</hi> being at an end, but there being no end of the <hi>malice</hi> of our Enemies, but the <hi>ſlaverie</hi> of the Nation; and the <hi>ruine</hi> of all thoſe <hi>faithfull Patriots</hi> that hath hitherto hindred it.</p>
            <p>They convert now their whole induſtry to the mannage of that Maxime <hi>(Divide and Rule)</hi> as to the only <hi>Engine</hi> left them to attaine their ends, yet this is not now <hi>firſt</hi> in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116281:4"/>practice amongſt them, it hath had its part during all the time of the Warre (though not ſo ſtrenuouſly purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, while they had other hopes) by raiſing and fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of factions, and diviſions in all places, Armies, Councels, <hi>Cajoling</hi> all ſorts by all thoſe <hi>Artifices,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their <hi>Intereſts, humours,</hi> and <hi>diſcontents</hi> might be wrought upon. Thus they have had their <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der every <hi>diſguiſe,</hi> who have laboured to divide the people among themſelves; and <hi>Characterize</hi> that divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by <hi>diſtinguiſhing Names,</hi> and to divide them all from the <hi>Parliament</hi> by ſeverall pretences; that it being naked of the <hi>protection of their force,</hi> might be unable <hi>to protect the people</hi> by <hi>their Authority.</hi> The Pulpits have ſerved the Kings Intereſt, while they thought they purſued their owne. (The Inſtruments putting them on, being a <hi>New Malignant party, under a diſguiſe,</hi> they not diſcerning they were acted by the old one, through the entremiſe of theſe,) and while they have divided the people, they have left them leſſe able to defend themſelves: Diviſion among themſelvs is not al, they divide alſo from the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament:</hi> for the people being wont to believe what ever they hear from <hi>that place, by thoſe men,</hi> have from thence been abated in their <hi>reſpect and opinion</hi> of the <hi>Parliament. Hence</hi> the City Remonſtrance, and <hi>hence</hi> the firſt <hi>viſible</hi> turne to their Actings toward the <hi>Parliament:</hi> The <hi>ſame Inſtruments</hi> tell the ſouldiers of their Arrears, ſtrengthen their <hi>reflections</hi> upon their <hi>merit,</hi> help them to <hi>heighten</hi> the ſenſe of their <hi>preſent wants,</hi> and <hi>ſufferings,</hi> and in the meane time labour all they can poſſibly, both in the Houſes, and among the people, to hinder the <hi>advancing or levie of moneys to ſatisfie them.</hi> And what workings there hath been, both toward, and in the Army under the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116281:4"/>Command of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> to breed faction and diviſion there, to irritate it, or to break it, by <hi>whom</hi> it was done, and whoſe intereſt <hi>thoſe men</hi> carried on, all men know. And how incredible ſoever it ſeem, yet even the <hi>Cries for liberty,</hi> endeavors of <hi>levellin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> perfectly play the Kings Game; his <hi>Tyranny</hi> can with greater eaſe over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow a <hi>levell,</hi> then where it meets with the oppoſition of the power of the Kingdom in the Parliament. The <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of thoſe deſignes,</hi> know that it is impoſſible for <hi>Tyranny</hi> ever to grow again upon Us, till <hi>that power be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, or diſabled,</hi> by which it hath been broken, and our right recovered; and that ſo long as the people ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their <hi>Protectors,</hi> and own their <hi>Protection,</hi> they will be ſafe under it. The <hi>Woolves</hi> perſwade the <hi>Sheep,</hi> if the <hi>Dogs</hi> were away, there would be a happy peace between them. The difficulty now is, to make the Sheep believe they are <hi>Woolves</hi> that make <hi>the overture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, tis the greateſt pity in the world that plain and ſimple integrity, and well-meaning innocency ſhould be deceived. But their <hi>unhappineſſe is,</hi> there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing eaſier; it is neceſſary the Serpent &amp; the Dove ſhould go together, elſe he that only conſults his own <hi>Candor and Integrity,</hi> will never believe that another mans <hi>Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions or Deſigns</hi> have any worſe <hi>principle.</hi> When <hi>Abſolon</hi> went about to dethrone his father, there followed him three hundred men from Jeruſalem, that went in the ſimplicity of their hearts, <hi>knowing nothing:</hi> the man pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended only a Religious Vow, and theſe poor, believed him, And every age produceth <hi>ſufficient numbers</hi> of as <hi>little foreſight;</hi> and there is no doubt, but if many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe that promote <hi>the dividing deſtructive A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of the people,</hi> and indeavor an <hi>Anarchicall level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116281:5"/>had had but as much light to have judged the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns</hi> of their <hi>leaders,</hi> and to have <hi>foreſeen</hi> the <hi>end</hi> of their motions, as they have <hi>good meaning,</hi> their Muſters had never ſwelled to the numbers they account them, though in that there is very little credit to be given to their own <hi>Roll.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It hath not been the leaſt part of the <hi>Art</hi> of thoſe that drive on theſe deſigns, to imploy ſuch to ſerve their turns, whoſe former <hi>merit</hi> might ſeem to <hi>priviledge a miſtake in their duty,</hi> and that it muſt be <hi>ingratitude</hi> at leaſt, if not <hi>cruelty</hi> in the Parliament to proceed to any ſevere animadverſion againſt men of ſo much <hi>merit</hi> as the Leaders, or ſo large and <hi>good affection</hi> as their followers.</p>
            <p>In which <hi>Stratagem,</hi> they have not failed, for by the Parliaments <hi>lenity and forbearance</hi> toward ſuch men, (in hope they would <hi>ſee their miſtakes,</hi> and return to the wayes of their duty and ſafety,) they are grown to that height, both by making <hi>Combinations;</hi> Printing and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſing all manner of <hi>falſe and ſcandalous Pamphlets and Papers</hi> againſt the Parliament, to debauch the reſt of the people, gathering <hi>monyes,</hi> and making <hi>Treaſurers and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentons</hi> of themſelves, as it is neceſſary to obviate by preſent and effectuall means. And the Parliament can no longer ſuffer them in theſe <hi>ſeditious wayes,</hi> without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting their truſt in preſerving the Peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the freedome and property of peaceable men.</p>
            <p>Among all the Inſtruments they have <hi>out-witted</hi> to carry on their deſigns with this ſort of people, there are none have viſibly done them more ſervice then Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Col. <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> a man who hath made himſelfe <hi>ſufficiently</hi> known to the world, by thoſe heaps of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Books and Papers that he hath either written, or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116281:5"/>owned againſt the Houſe of Peers, and ſuch as have <hi>done him greateſt courteſies;</hi> filled with <hi>falſhoods, bitterneſſe,</hi> and <hi>ingratitude,</hi> whereby he hath given himſelf a <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter</hi> ſufficient to diſtinguiſh him (with the Judicious) from a man walking according to the <hi>rules of ſobriety,</hi> and the <hi>juſt deportment of a Chriſtian:</hi> 'Tis true, he ſuffered much from the Biſhops, in the time of their exorbitancies, and he was one of the firſt the Parliament took into their care for liberty and redreſſe. But the preſent temper of his ſpirit, gives ſome ground to beleeve, that he added much to the weight of his preſſures, by his want of meekneſſe to bear what Providence had laid him under.</p>
            <p>'Tis alſo true, that he hath done good ſervice for the Parliament, and adventured his life, and loſt of his blood in the Common Cauſe. But ſome that know him, well obſerve, that he brought not the <hi>ſame affections from Oxford,</hi> that he was carried priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thither withall; though indeed he hath alſo done ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ſince that time. And the Parliament hath not been unmindfull either of his ſufferings, or of his ſervices, but hath given him ſeverall ſums of money, notwithſtanding the Committee of Accounts reported to the Houſe, that in their judgements there was nothing due to him.</p>
            <p>But let his ſervices be as <hi>great</hi> as himſelf, or his friends will have them, yet 'tis poſſible for a man to reflect <hi>too much</hi> upon his <hi>own deſert;</hi> and mens <hi>overvaluing</hi> their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, have oftentimes produced ſuch ſubſequent Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as have buried their firſt <hi>merit in a puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is very probable, many of thoſe that he miſleads into theſe dangerous Actions, look upon him as a <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> in the Cauſe againſt the Biſhops; and believe that all his zeal is only for the promotion of <hi>Righteouſneſſe, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116281:6"/>juſt things,</hi> and for the Vindicating and Aſſerting the peoples liberty againſt Oppreſſion and Violence, and that only by <hi>Petition,</hi> and indubitably juſt, and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed way for all men to ſeek their grievances by, and by which they may without offence, addreſſe to any <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity or greatneſſe whatſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To take off this <hi>diſguiſe,</hi> and diſabuſe well meaning men, who cannot judge him by his <hi>Character</hi> drawn <hi>of himſelf, by himſelf,</hi> in his ſeverall books; It will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to give the world a Narrative of what his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment and carriage was toward the Houſe of Peers, upon which he was impriſoned, it having yet been ſpread to the World, only as he and his friends have pleaſed to <hi>dreſſe it,</hi> all which is taken out of the Records of that Houſe, and is as followeth.</p>
            <p>UPon the publiſhing of a Book by him written, called, <hi>The juſt mans Iuſtification,</hi> and complaint thereof made to the Houſe; It was Ordered the 10. of <hi>Iune,</hi> 1646. That Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Iohn Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne</hi> ſhall appeare, and anſwer ſuch things as he ſtands charged with, concerning a Book entituled, <hi>The juſt mans Iuſtification.</hi> The 11. of <hi>Iune</hi> he appeared, and there delivered at the Barre a paper, entituled, <hi>The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation,</hi> Plea, and Defence of Lieut. Col. <hi>Iohn Lilborn,</hi> given to the Lords at their Barre, the 11. of <hi>Iune,</hi> 1646. with his Appeal to his proper and legall Tryers, and Judges, the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England</hi> aſſembled in <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> In which Proteſtation, after he hath acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged an Obligation to the Houſe, for dealing juſtly and honourably with him in a Parliamentary way, in a buſineſſe of his, lately before that Houſe, yet that he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116281:6"/>would not ſubmit to any Judgement of this Houſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in a criminall Cauſe; but would rather under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe all deaths or miſeries which the wit of man can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, or his power and Tyranny inflict; And cloſeth his Proteſtation in theſe words, Therefore doe from you, and from your Bar, as Inchroachers and uſurping Judges, appeal to the Barre, and Tribunal of my competent, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and legall Tryers and Judges, the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> aſſembled in <hi>Parliament:</hi> which Proteſtation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrived, and prepared by him upon premeditation, and given in at the Barre with ſo much contempt of and affront unto the Priviledges of this Houſe, It was upon conſideration thereof had, Ordered that the ſaid Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Collonel <hi>Iohn Lilborn</hi> ſhould ſtand committed to Newgate, for bringing into the Houſe a ſcandalous and contemptuous paper, And that the Keeper of Newgate doe keep him in ſafe cuſtody.</p>
            <p>The 23. of <hi>Iune</hi> following, the Houſe Ordered he ſhould be brought into the Houſe as a Delinquent, being formerly committed as a Delinquent. At which time being brought to the Barre according to the ſaid Order, he refuſed there to kneele, which is the conſtant po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and ſo known to be; and accordingly practiſed by all who are ſent for as Delinquents by either of the Houſes. And upon that refuſall, the Houſe Ordered, That he ſhould for that his contempt to the Houſe, be committed cloſe priſoner to Newgate, And that none be ſuffered to reſort to him, nor any pen and inke to be allowed him, untill the Houſe ſhould take further Order therein, And it was then further Ordered, That the Kings Counſell, with the aſſiſtance of Mr. <hi>Hailes,</hi> Mr. <hi>Herne,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Glover,</hi> ſhould draw up a Charge againſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116281:7"/>him with all convenient ſpeed, and that they ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe with the Judges herein, and acquaint them with precedents: Which Charge being by the ſaid Councell drawn up into certaine Articles, and brought into the Houſe by Mr. <hi>Nathaniel Finch,</hi> his Majeſties Serjeant at Law. <hi>Iuly</hi> 10. Containing matter of high crimes, and miſdemeanors, (and ſuch as only concerned the Houſe of Peers in the Priviledges thereof, and ſome of their Members, of which matters, We are certainly the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable and undoubted Judges) which Charge was then and there read. And it was then Ordered, That the ſaid <hi>Iohn, Lilborne</hi> ſhould be brought to the Barre next day, which was done accordingly. And he being there, was required to kneel at the Barre (as is uſuall in ſuch caſes) and to hear his Charge read, that he might make his defence thereto; he did not only refuſe to kneel, as before he had done, but when the Houſe command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Charge to be read, he ſaid he would not hear, and upon reading thereof he ſtopped his eares with his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Being commanded to withdraw (after the Houſe had taken this his contemptuous carriage into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) it was Ordered, That he ſhould be called in again, and admoniſhed, and told, that by his ſtopping of his ears, his ill language, and contemptuous and ſcornfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, he had deprived himſelf of what favour he might have had in the Houſe. And commanded him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine without ſtopping of his ears to hear his Charge. He anſwered, he had appealed from this Houſe (as not his competent Judges) to the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> to which he would ſtand ſo long as he had any bloud in his body. The Houſe again commands his Charge to be read, and he again told them he would not hear it, And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116281:7"/>he again ſtopped his eares while it was readings being asked what he ſaid to his Charge, he anſwered he heard nothing of it, had nothing to doe with it, tooke no notice of it, but would ſtand to his Proteſtation, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving appealed from this Houſe, and proteſted againſt it, as unrighteous Judges, to thoſe Judges who were to judge him and them, namely the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in <hi>Parliament.</hi> Being again commanded to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, the Houſe took his refuſall as an Anſwer <hi>pro Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſo</hi> to the whole matter of his Charge. And taking in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conſideration, the high contempt to the honour and dignity of the Houſe of Peers, ſhewed by his words and ſpeeches at the Barre, which were alſo contained in his Charge. It was amongſt other things adjudged, That Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Iohn Lilborne</hi> for his high contempt to the honour of the Houſe, ſhould be impriſoned in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> during the pleaſure of the Houſe. And upon conſideration of the whole matter of his Charge, it was likewiſe amongſt other things adjudged, that he be impriſoned ſeven years.</p>
            <p>Had this <hi>Contemptuous carriage</hi> been ſhewed to the <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Court</hi> in the Kingdome, or to a <hi>ſingle</hi> Juſtice of the Peace, he would certainly have been committed for <hi>misbehaviour.</hi> Courts and Magiſtrates are no longer able to execute the duty of their places, and diſcharge their truſt in the adminiſtration of Juſtice, than they keep up and maintain their <hi>Dignity and Authority</hi> from the tramp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and contempt of <hi>Delinquents.</hi> And there is no doubt but theſe <hi>approaches</hi> made by Lieutenant Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Iohn Lilborne,</hi> and carried even within the walls of the Lords Houſe <hi>with ſo little loſſe,</hi> was a maine encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to that generall <hi>aſſault and force</hi> upon both
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116281:8"/>Houſes, upon the 26. of <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt, by that Rable of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formadoes, and of the Prentices ſet on and encouraged, by the <hi>known Malignant</hi>-then-<hi>ruling-part of the City.</hi> This carriage of his might ſeem ſufficient to <hi>diſcover</hi> the Man, and being known, might warn every well-tempered and peaceable diſpoſition, to take heed of engaging in any Deſigne that may be the conception of <hi>ſuch a Spirit:</hi> the birth whereof can portend nothing but Diſtraction and confuſion. And the better yet to <hi>undeceive</hi> wel-meaning men, who may perhaps believe the Reſults and productions of the late frequent, and numerous meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of him, and his party, in and about the City, are of a contrary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omplexion and tendency, and can ſerve no other end than a firme and ſpeedy ſetling the peace and tranquillity of the Kingdome, which all good men deſire and ſhould promote; They may here take notice of what was delivered to the Houſes of <hi>Parliament,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Maſterſon</hi> Miniſter of Shoreditch, who was <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> at one of thoſe meetings, And which was alſo (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many <hi>denials, tergiverſations</hi> and <hi>prevarications,</hi> by the ſaid Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Iohn Lilborne,</hi> and the lie given (or words that ſignified as much) to Mr. <hi>Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> in the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> (who was confronted there with him at the Barre) <hi>confeſſed</hi> by <hi>himſelfe,</hi> in <hi>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular one only excepted.</hi> The whole Relation whereof is here printed from the Copie, ſigned by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Maſterſon</hi> with his own hand, and is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="report">
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:116281:8"/>
                        <head>At a meeting in <hi>Well-Yard,</hi> in, or neer <hi>Wapping,</hi> at the houſe of one <hi>Williams</hi> a Gardiner, on Monday the 17 of <hi>Ianuary.</hi> 1647.</head>
                        <p>THere were Aſſembled Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Iohn Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn, Iohn Wildman,</hi> (with many others) debating a Petition, when I and one <hi>Robert Malbor</hi> of <hi>Shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditch</hi> Pariſh came in; anon after we entred the Room, one Lieutenant <hi>Lever</hi> Objected againſt the manner of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and ſaid, That he liked well enough the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the Petition, but he did not like the manner (namely) of Petitioning the Houſe of Commons, for (ſaid he) <hi>They have never done us any Right, nor will they ever do us any:</hi> To this Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> Anſwered, <hi>We muſt, ſaid he, own ſome viſible Authority for the preſent, or elſe we ſhall be brought to Ruine and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion: but when we have raiſed up the ſpirits of the people through the whole Kingdom</hi> whether it be nine dayes hence, or a moneth, or three moneths, when the Houſe ſhall be fit to receive an Impreſsion of Juſtice) We ſhall <hi>FORCE. them to grant us thoſe things we deſire.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> did then and there Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That the People of <hi>London</hi> had appointed ten or twelve of their Commiſsioners, (whereof he the ſaid <hi>Lilburn</hi> was one) though he ſaid likewiſe, that the honeſt Blades in <hi>Southwark</hi> did not like the word Commiſsioners. Theſe Commiſsioners were appointed to promote the Petition, and ſend out Agents into every City, Town, and Pariſh, if they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116281:9"/>could poſsibly) of every County of the Kingdome, to inform the people of their Liberties and Priviledges; and not only to get their hands to the Petition, for (ſaid he) I would not give three pence for ten thouſand hands.</p>
                        <p>A plain man of the Company Objected againſt that way of Proceeding, thus: <hi>Mr.</hi> Lilburn (ſaid he) <hi>we know that the generality of the People are wicked, and if (by the ſending abroad of your Agents into all the Pariſhes of the Kingdom) they come to have power and ſtrength in their hand, We may ſuppoſe, and fear they will cut the throats of all thoſe who are called <hi>Roundheads,</hi> that is, the honeſt, godly, faithfull men in the Land. Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Colonel</hi> Lilburn <hi>Anſwered,</hi> Piſh (ſaid he) do not you fear that, he that hath this Petition in his hand, and a Blue Ribb and in his Hat, need not fear his throat cutting; or this Petition in your hand, will be as good as a Blue Ribband in your Hat to preſerve your throat from cutting. It was further Objected by one of the Company that ſat at, or neer the upper end of the Table, That it was not fit to diſturb (or to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) the Houſe at this time, ſeeing they had made ſuch excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Votes concerning the King, and had appointed a Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee to hear, and report all our grievances. Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lilburn</hi> Anſwered, <hi>Do you know, ſaid he, how thoſe Votes were procured?</hi> (or words to that effect.) Some An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, No; nor did they care, ſince the Votes (as they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended) were ſo excellent; Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lilburn</hi> ſaid he could tell them. There was (ſaid he) a bargain ſtruck be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Crumwell, Ireton,</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> and the bargain was this, They (namely Lieutenant Generall <hi>Crumwell,</hi> and Commiſſary Generall <hi>Ireton</hi>) by their influence on the Army, ſhould eſtate the <hi>King</hi> in his Throne, Power, and Authority; and for their Reward, <hi>Crumwell</hi> ſhould receive
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116281:9"/>(or had received) a Blue Ribband from the <hi>King,</hi> and be made Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and his ſon <hi>Ireton,</hi> either Lord Lieutenant, or Field Marſhall of <hi>Ireland:</hi> and this he (the ſaid Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lilburn</hi>) ſaid he would make good to all the world.</p>
                        <p>Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lilburn</hi> ſaid further, that certain In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of this comming to a Member of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, our good for beſt) friend: I need not name him, ſaid he, I ſuppoſe you all know him; his father was a Parliament man, and a Knight, but he is dead, and this Gentleman his ſon is of his Chriſtian name (as they call it) a man of a good Eſtate. This Gentleman, ſaid he, takes upon him a noble <hi>Felton</hi> reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that (rather then a Kingdome ſhould be inſlaved to the luſt of one man) he would diſpatch him (namely <hi>Crumwell</hi>) wherever he met him, though in the preſence of the Generall Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> himſelf, and for that end, provided, and <hi>charged a Piſtoll, and took a Dagger in his Pocket, that if the one did not, the other ſhould diſpatch him.</hi> The ſaid Lieut. Col. <hi>Iohn Lilburn,</hi> (being asked how it came to paſſe that he did not effect it, and Act according to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution? Anſwered, The Gentleman (ſaid he) communicating his reſolution to a Member of the Houſe of Commons, a Knight whom he judged faithfull, the Gentleman was by this Knight ſhut up in his Chamber in White Hall a whole day; and the Knight diſpatched an expreſſe to <hi>Crumwell,</hi> to inform him of the Gentlemans Reſolution; whereupon, <hi>Crumwell</hi> (ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending his perſon in danger) called a pretended day of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation; there he was reconciled to the Officers of the Army, drew up a Declaration to the Houſe, which begat and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thoſe Votes. Vpon this <hi>John Wildman</hi> ſaid, <hi>That he knew three other men (at the ſame time) had taken up the ſame Reſolution of killing</hi> Crumwell, <hi>and there was not one of them that knew the Intentions of another:</hi>
                           <pb n="16" facs="tcp:116281:10"/>likewiſe the ſaid <hi>Iohn Wildman</hi> ſaid, <hi>That he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver truſt honeſt man again for</hi> Crumwels <hi>ſake.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lilburn,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Iohn Wildman</hi> (ſpeaking promiſcuouſly in the Commendation of the ſaid Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) one or other or both of them affirmed, That this Petition was of more worth and value, then any thing they had ever yet attempted; and that ſome <hi>great Malignants</hi> (as they are called) told them, that if they were not ingaged to the perſon of this King, and had perſonally ſerved him, they would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage with them; and the <hi>ſaid Malignants gave them incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement</hi> to go on with it, ſaying, it was the <hi>moſt rationall piece</hi> that they had ſeen: And that they (the people aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled) might underſtand how the Petition had wrought alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, they affirmed that it (the Petition) had made the Lords Houſe to quake, and the Commons themſelves to ſtinke: and that before the Petition was two dayes old, or had been two dayes abroad, the Lords (I ſhall not need to name them, ſaid he, but the greateſt Earls of them in Eſtate, in Authority and Popularity) ſent to us a creature of their own to Article with us, and offered (ſo we would deſiſt-from promoting the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) to conſent to all our priviledges and liberties that we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired in our Petition, ſo that we would abate them their Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative power. Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lilburn</hi> ſaid further, When they ſaw we would not deſist, they (the Lords) offered us thirty thouſand pounds, if we would yet ſit down, and lay the Petition aſide: nay, more ſaid he, but here the ſaid <hi>John Wildman</hi> interrupted him, and ſaid, Prethee do not tell all, but <hi>Lilburn</hi> replied, He would, and they ſhould hereby ſee their (the Lords) baſeneſſe, whereupon going on, he ſaid, This morning they ſent to this Gentlemans Chamber (laying his hand upon <hi>Wildman</hi>) at the <hi>Sarazens head</hi> in <hi>Friday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> and offered him, that if we would forbear to Promote
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116281:10"/>this Petition, they would be content for their heirs and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, to cut off the Legiſlative power from them by Ordinance or Act for ever, ſo we would let them quietly injoy the Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power for their lives.</p>
                        <p>Lieutenant Col. <hi>Lilburn</hi> told them, That they (the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners) had their conſtant meetings on Mondays, Wedneſdays, and Fridays in the evening at the <hi>Whalebone;</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther three dayes at <hi>Southwark, Wapping,</hi> and other places, with their friends; and that upon the next Lords day they were to meet at <hi>Dartfort</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> to receive an account of their Agents, (from <hi>Graveſend, Maidſtone,</hi> and moſt of the choice Townes in that County) how they had promoted the buſineſſe there.</p>
                        <p>Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lilburn</hi> drawing a Paper-Book from under his ſhort Red Coat, and turning over the leaves of it, told them that there were certain Letters, one to Colonel <hi>Blunt,</hi> another (as I remember) to Sir <hi>Anthony Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den;</hi> and that he ſaid, he wrote himſelf likewiſe divers Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to our friends the well-affected of ſuch and ſuch a County, whoſe names I remembred not: he the ſaid (Lieutenant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel) told them likewiſe, That becauſe the buſineſſe muſt needs be a work of charge (there being <hi>thirty thouſand</hi> Petitions to come forth in Print to morrow, and it would coſt money to ſend their Agents abroad, though the honeſt ſouldiers now at <hi>White Hall</hi> would ſave them ſomething in ſcattering them up and down in the Counties) they had therefore appointed Treaſurers, namely Mr. <hi>Prince,</hi> Mr. <hi>Chidly,</hi> and others, and Collectors, (whoſe names as I remember, he did not reade) who ſhould gather up from thoſe that acted with them, of ſome two pence, three pence, ſix pence, a ſhilling, two ſhillings, half a Crown a week: and thus promiſing to meet them the next night, he tooke leave.</p>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:116281:11"/>
                        <p>But immediately before his departure told them, that they ſhut him up in the Tower the night before, but they ſhould not have his company theſe fourteen nights for it. This is the ſumme and ſence of that which was delivered, and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Houſe of Lords, at the conference, and in the <hi>Commons</hi> Houſe by</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Geo: Maſterſon.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>BY this teſtimony of Mr. <hi>Maſterſon</hi> (which was all but <hi>one particular,</hi> as was ſaid before, confeſſed by Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> himſelfe) Its hoped all men truly conſcientious will take heed how they comply with theſe men, who have conceived thoſe <hi>black deſignes</hi> in the dark, and think to bring them forth by <hi>murders and aſſaſsination;</hi> certainly theſe Councels look as if they were ſuggeſted from him that is <hi>a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer from the beginning,</hi> and yet many are drawn into the ſame guilt, danger, and diſſervice to the peace of the Kingdome. The <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> ſeemes to be <hi>formed,</hi> and the <hi>actings to</hi> be <hi>at hand, Treaſurers</hi> choſen, <hi>Collectors</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>moneys</hi> gathered, <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> ſent abroad to ſtirre up the people; <hi>Murders and aſſaſsinations</hi> are undertaken, and <hi>Lilburn,</hi> and <hi>Wildman know the Inſtruments.</hi> Can any man now that deſire to have Peace, and proſperity ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and conſerved, and that abhorres to think of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of all things,</hi> and the <hi>effuſions of innocent bloud,</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if the <hi>Parliament</hi> takes care in diſcharge of their Truſt, to make abortive theſe <hi>monſtrous conceptions,</hi> and prevent the like for the <hi>future,</hi> by preſent <hi>ſecuring</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>to puniſhing</hi> the Authors of <hi>theſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſay any thing further upon this relation ſeems
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116281:11"/>needleſſe, it being not imaginable, That after ſo clear and full a diſcovery, there ſhould be found any man, either ſo <hi>ſimple,</hi> or ſo <hi>wicked,</hi> as not to <hi>diſcover</hi> the <hi>monſter</hi> under the <hi>mask,</hi> to ſee the danger, hate the deſign, and <hi>feare the Event;</hi> and that will not flie from the Councels &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of theſe <hi>Peſts</hi> and <hi>Incendiaries,</hi> who while they cal themſelvs <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> do yet <hi>project,</hi> or elſe at leaſt <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal,</hi> and <hi>applaud deſigned murthers and aſsaſsinations.</hi> And that all men may the better ſee, what is like to be the end to which theſe actions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>end, let them here take this account given from a ſure hand in forreign parts, Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that a Prieſt, a Chaplaine of a forrain Miniſter of State, whoſe name (which is to be concealed) ſeemes to make him an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, was lately employed hither as a <hi>Spie,</hi> and at his returne gives this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to his Maſter, and to other Confidents, That there are <hi>foure hundred Miſsionaries</hi> now in <hi>London,</hi> and in the <hi>Army,</hi> under <hi>ſeverall diſguiſes,</hi> and that ſome of them <hi>act the Preacher,</hi> all which, with all diligence attend the ſervice of their Miſſion, with hope to give a very good account to their Superiours: Are not theſe Deſignes, theſe Councels, and the violent carrying thereof, more like to be the Doctrine of thoſe <hi>Wolves</hi> under <hi>Sheeps skins,</hi> than of any man that hath reſigned up himſelf to be led by the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>But that which covers all is, that you doe but Petition, and addreſſe to the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> with much ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>reſpect</hi> and <hi>deferencie.</hi> But, what <hi>account</hi> you make of their Authority, is ſeen by Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burns</hi> Anſwer to Lieutenant <hi>Level</hi> his Objection, and <hi>what account</hi> of all the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath done, in aſſerting and vindicating the juſt freedome of the Nation, is ſeen
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116281:12"/>in the ſaid objection. And <hi>how farre</hi> you meane to <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon,</hi> and <hi>acquieſce</hi> in the Judgement of the Houſe, to which you addreſſe, is likewiſe ſeen in ſome of the Letters mentioned by Mr. <hi>Maſterſon,</hi> to be ſent to their friends, the wel-affected of ſuch and ſuch a County. That, to all the peaceable and wel-minded people in <hi>Kent,</hi> who deſire preſent Peace, Freedome, Juſtice, and common Right, and good of all men, is, as followeth, the Originall whereof is ready to be produced when oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion is.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Worthy Gentlemen, and dear Friends,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>OVr bowels are troubled, and our hearts pained within us, to behold the Diviſions, Diſtractions, heart-bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and contentions which abound in this diſtreſſed Nation, and we are confounded in our ſelves upon the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of the confuſion and deſolation, which will be the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain conſequence of ſuch diviſions, if they ſhould be but for a little time longer continued; there are now clouds of bloud o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our heads again, and the very rumors and fears of Warre hath ſo waſted Trading, and enhaunſed the price of all food and cloathing, that Famine is even entring into your gates; and doubtleſſe, neither pen nor tongue can expreſſe the miſery, which will enſue immediately upon the beginning of another Warre; Why therefore O our Country men, ſhould we not every man ſay each to other, as <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Lot,</hi> or <hi>Moſes</hi> to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116281:12"/>the two Iſraelites, Why ſhould we contend each with other, ſeeing we are brethren? O that our advice might be acceptable to you, that you would every man expoſtulate each with other, and now while you have an opportunity, conſider together, wherefore the contention hath been theſe ſix or ſeven years! Hath it not been for freedome and Iuſtice? O then propound each to other the chief principles of your freedome, and the foundation of Iuſtice, and common Right, and queſtionleſſe, when you ſhall underſtand the deſires each of other, you will unite together inviolably to purſue them.</p>
                  <p>Now truely in our apprehenſions, this work is prepared to your hands in the Fetition, which we herewith ſend to you; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, if you ſhall all joyne together to follow reſolutely, and unweariedly, after the things contained in that Petition, the bloud and confuſion which now threaten us may be prevented, and the ſweet ſtreames of Iuſtice will run into your boſomes freely without obſtruction; O that the Lord may be ſo propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to this tottering Nation, as to give you to underſtand theſe things which belong to your Peace and welfare!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Many honeſt people are reſolved already to unite together in that Petition, &amp; to proſecute the obtaining it with all their ſtrength; they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, that now after ſeven years waiting for Juſtice, Peace, and Freedome, they will receive no deniall in theſe requeſts</hi> which are ſo eſſentiall to their Peace and Freedome; and for the more effectuall procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116281:13"/>in this buſineſſe, there is a Method and Order ſetled in all the Wards in <hi>London,</hi> and the out Pariſhes and Suburbs; they have appointed ſeverall active men in every Ward and Diviſion, to be a <hi>Committee,</hi> to take the ſpeciall care of the buſineſſe, and to appoint active men in every Pariſh, to read the Petition at ſet meetings for that purpoſe, and to take Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, and to move as many as can poſsibly, to goe in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon when the day of delivering it ſhall be appointed; and they intend to give notice of that time to all the adjacent Counties, that as many of them as poſsibly can, may alſo joyne with them the ſame day; and the like orderly way of proceeding is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to ſeverall Counties, to whom the Petition is ſent, as to <hi>Hartfordſhier, Buckingham, Oxford, Cambridge, Rut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landſhier, &amp;c.</hi> And we cannot but propound to you the ſame Method, as the beſt expedient for your union, in purſuing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſpeedy ſettlement of your Peace and Freedome, therefore in brief we deſire,</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> That you would appoint meetings in every Diviſion of your County, and there to ſelect faithfull men of publick ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, to take care that the Petition be ſent to the hands of the moſt active men in every Town, to unite the Town in thoſe deſires of common right, and to take their ſubſcriptions.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> That you would appoint as many as can with conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, to meet at <hi>Dartford,</hi> the <hi>23.</hi> of this preſent <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary,</hi> being Lords day, and we ſhall conferre with you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Matters that concerne your Peace, and common good and Freedome.</p>
                  <p>Wee ſhall at preſent adde no more but this, that to ſerve
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116281:13"/>you, and our whole countrey in whatſoever concerns its common peace and well fare, is, and alwayes ſhall be, the deſire and joy of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your moſt Faithfull Friends and Servants which came from London from many other friends upon this Service,</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Iohn Lilburn.</item>
                           <item>Wildman.</item>
                           <item>Iohn Davies.</item>
                           <item>Richard Woodward.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>Dartford <date>this 9. of <hi>Ian.</hi> 1647.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>VVell minded People,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOU who are apt to <hi>reſolve</hi> and <hi>Act</hi> upon the bare conſultation of your own <hi>unexperienced</hi> innocency, look to your ſelves, <hi>there is a deſign upon you;</hi> you perhaps cannot believe, that this <hi>tenderneſſe</hi> and <hi>trouble of Bowels</hi> profeſſed, ſhould tend to <hi>tear</hi> out your owne; that theſe <hi>breathings</hi> after <hi>Juſtice</hi> ſhould <hi>ſubject</hi> you to the <hi>worſt Tyranny,</hi> and that theſe men are reducing the Kingdome into <hi>Atomes,</hi> while they cry out, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of <hi>Diviſion;</hi> but a <hi>Poyſon</hi> is offered you in this <hi>ſweet wine,</hi> and all theſe <hi>ſugred words</hi> ſerve but to <hi>ſweeten
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116281:14"/>that Pill</hi> in your mouth, which will be <hi>bitterneſſe</hi> in your belly; there is a <hi>book</hi> in the Bait, and all thoſe ſeeming prudentiall directions in the cloſe of this Letter, ſerve but to teach you how to deſtroy your ſelves with the greateſt <hi>dexterity</hi> and <hi>infallibility. The poyſon is in the middle,</hi> which (if you will take theſe <hi>State-Montebanks</hi> words) many honeſt people are reſolved already to take, that is, <hi>To unite together in the Petition, and to proſecute the obtaining of it with all their ſtrength; and they are determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that now after ſo long waiting for Iuſtice, Peace, and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, they will receive no deny all in theſe requeſts:</hi> Here's the ſecond part of the 26 of <hi>Iuly,</hi> to the ſame Tune to a ſyllable: There was a <hi>Petition,</hi> and ſo is here; there was an <hi>Vnion of the Rabble,</hi> ſo here muſt be an <hi>Vnion;</hi> there was an Horrid, and Barbarous force and violence; here muſt be a Proſecution with <hi>all their ſtrength:</hi> The people of divers whole Counties ſolicited to be preſent at the delivery of it, and muſt be ingaged to it by <hi>preſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions:</hi> Can this, <hi>all their ſtrength, all this number,</hi> this determination <hi>to take no deniall,</hi> be leſſe then a <hi>War,</hi> or leſſe then a <hi>forcing of the Legiſlative power?</hi> Be warned to take heed of ſuch dayes works as the 26 of <hi>Iuly,</hi> it <hi>hath,</hi> and <hi>will</hi> coſt ſome <hi>dear:</hi> Only the difference is, The Actors in this intended Rebellious and Treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble force, in the judgement of theſe <hi>infallible Cenſors</hi> of <hi>Piety and Honeſty,</hi> muſt be honeſt men: But if they be men ſo qualified, let them take heed of this Conſpiracy, that they may continue ſo ſtill, and let not thoſe himble <hi>Preſligiators juggle</hi> them into <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Treaſon,</hi> before they conſider whither they are going.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:116281:14"/>
                  <p>The Truth is, you mean to ſtir up the people, and make <hi>your ſelves the leaders;</hi> and then 'tis not <hi>one man alone</hi> that wil be armed with <hi>Pisiol</hi> and <hi>Dagger.</hi> And it will not be then, either a <hi>Blue Riband in the Hat,</hi> nor <hi>a Petition in the Hand,</hi> that wil be a ſufficient defence to any of thoſe, whoſe either <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Conſcience, Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Judgment, Integrity</hi> and <hi>ſenſe of Duty,</hi> or <hi>more large Eſtate,</hi> and <hi>deſire to defend his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety,</hi> ſhal have made them the <hi>object</hi> of your <hi>bevelling fury.</hi> But any one of <hi>thoſe qualifications</hi> may make a man as guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to you, as to <hi>write</hi> and <hi>read</hi> did <hi>thoſe,</hi> who had the <hi>unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of ſo much learning</hi> in the days of your <hi>Predeceſsors, Iack Straw</hi> and his <hi>Aſsociats.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But let us examine your Petition it ſelf, magnified, as <hi>Lilburn</hi> and <hi>Wildman</hi> affirm, by the greateſt Malignants, for the moſt <hi>rational Peace they had ſeen,</hi> and which they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them by all means <hi>to promote,</hi> an acknowledgment of theirs to be ſpecially noted, they have never yet been ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the <hi>peace of the People,</hi> if it took not <hi>beginning</hi> from their <hi>ſuggeſtions,</hi> 'tis certainly <hi>promoted by their help.</hi> They alſo giving out that <hi>noman</hi> is more the Kings then <hi>Lilburn;</hi> And 'tis known to all, that while <hi>Lilburn</hi> was in the Tower, he ſtill maintained a cloſe Converſation and aquaintance with the principle dangerous men, and eſpecially with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid Jenkins,</hi> now a priſoner in <hi>New-gate</hi> for his <hi>Treaſons.</hi> But if it be a Petition to the Houſe, why is it Printed and Publiſhed to the <hi>people,</hi> before the preſenting of it to the <hi>Houſe?</hi> Is it to get the approbation of <hi>multitudes?</hi> What need of that? If what is asked be <hi>reaſonable</hi> and <hi>juſt,</hi> and <hi>good for the publike,</hi> it needs <hi>no other qualiſication</hi> for its <hi>accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> nor <hi>arguments</hi> for its <hi>grant;</hi> though it were only the <hi>private ſuggeſtion</hi> of a <hi>ſingle man:</hi> If it be not ſo, the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, though very <hi>many more</hi> then wil <hi>own this,</hi> ought not to be <hi>gratiſied</hi> with the <hi>wrong</hi> of all the reſt. The <hi>whole Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the Kingdom, is in <hi>the Iudgment</hi> of the <hi>Houſes;</hi> you
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116281:15"/>can repreſent your <hi>own preſſures,</hi> but not thoſe of <hi>all the Kingdom,</hi> for <hi>you are not all the Kingdom.</hi> You may account that your <hi>preſſure,</hi> which others, and as many as you, may judg <hi>their benefit;</hi> and the Houſes truſted by all, muſt judg what is <hi>good for all.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the Supream Authority of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Commons Aſſembled in Parliament.</head>
                        <head type="sub">The earneſt Petition of many Free-born People of this Nation.</head>
                        <opener>SHEWETH,</opener>
                        <p>THAT the devouring fire of the Lords wrath, hath burnt in the bowels of this miſerable Nation, until its almoſt conſumed.</p>
                        <p>That upon a due ſearch into the cauſes of Gods heavy Judgments, we find <note n="a" place="margin">
                              <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ns</hi> 5.9, 10 11 12. <hi>Micah</hi> 2 2.3. <hi>Micah</hi> 3.3 4 9.10.11.12. <hi>Habba</hi> 2.8.17 <hi>Joel</hi> 3.3</note> that in juſtice and oppreſſion, have been the common Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal ſias, for which the Lord hath threatned woes, confuſions and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, unto any People or Nation; <hi>Woe</hi> (ſaith God) to <hi>the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing City.</hi> Zeph. <hi>3.1.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>That when the King had opened the Flood-gates of injuſtice and oppreſſion <note n="b" place="margin">See the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance of the State of the Kingdom, <hi>Decem.</hi> 1641. p. 5, 6, 7, 8 9 10, 11, 14, 15.</note> upon the people, and yet peremptorily declared that the people, who truſted him for their good, could not in, or by their Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m nt <hi>require any account of the diſcharge of his truſt;</hi> and when by a pretended <hi>negative vo ce</hi>
                           <note n="c" place="margin">See the Kings Anſwer to the Parliaments Remonſt. of May 19 1642. 1 part book Decla. page 254, 284, 285. See the Kings Anſwer to the <hi>Parl.</hi> Decla of May 26. 1642. page 298.</note> to Laws, he would not ſuffer the ſtrength of the Kingdom, <hi>the</hi>
                           <note n="d" place="margin">See the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance for the <hi>Militia, Feb.</hi> 1641 1 book Decla. page 89, &amp; pa. 96, 105 106. 114, 126, 175, 176, 182 243, 289, 292</note>
                           <hi>Militi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>,</hi> to be ſo diſpoſed of, that oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> might be ſafely remedied, &amp; oppreſſors brought to condign puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but raiſed a War <note n="e" place="margin">See the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Votes May 20, 1642 1 part Book Decla, 259, ſee alſo page 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>9, 576, 577, 580, 584, 617.</note> to protect the <hi>ſubvertors</hi> of our <hi>Laws and Libe ties,</hi> and maintain <hi>Himſelf</hi> to be ſubject to no <hi>accompt,</hi> even for ſuch oppreſſions, and purſuing after an oppreſſive power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Judg of the Earth, with whom the <hi>Throne of iniquity can have no fellowſhip, hath brought him low, and executed fierce wrath upon many of his ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>nts</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>That God expects Juſtice from thoſe <hi>before whoſe eyes he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed an unjuſt generation.</hi> Zeph. <hi>3.6.7.</hi> and without <hi>doing juſtly,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116281:15"/>and releeving the oppreſſed,</hi> God abhors <hi>faſtings and praye s,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts himſelf mocked. <hi>Eſa. 5 8.4 5, 6 7. Mic. 6.6, 7, 8.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>That our eyes fail with looking to ſee the Foundations of our Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Peace ſecured by this Honorable Houſe, and yet we are made to depend upon the <hi>Will</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Lords,</hi> which were never choſen or betruſted by the People, to redreſs their grievances. And this Honorable Houſe, which formerly declared, that they were the repreſentative of al <hi>England,</hi> &amp; betruſted with our Estates, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Lives, <hi>1</hi> part Book of <hi>Decla. 264.382.</hi> do now declare by their practiſe, that <hi>they will not redreſs</hi> our grievances, or ſettle our Freedoms, unleſs the King and the Lords will.</p>
                        <p>That in caſe you ſhould thus proceed, Parliaments wil be rendered wholly uſeleſs to the People, and their happineſs left to depend ſolely upon the <hi>Will</hi> of the King, and ſuch as he by his Patents creates Lords; and ſo the invaluable price <hi>of all the precious Engliſh blood; ſpilt in the defence of our freedoms</hi> againſt the <hi>King,</hi> ſhal be imbezelled or lost; and certainly, <hi>God the avenger of blood,</hi> wil require it of the <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructors of juſtice and freedom.</hi> Iudges <hi>9.24.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>That though our Petitions have been <hi>burned, and our perſons im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, reviled, and abuſed only for petitioning,</hi> yet we cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair abſolutely of all bowels of compaſſion in this Honorable Houſe, to an <hi>inſlaved periſhing people.</hi> We ſtill nouriſh ſome hopes, that you wil at laſt conſider that our <hi>eſtates</hi> are <hi>expended,</hi> the whole trade of the <hi>Nation decayed,</hi> thouſands of families impoveriſhed, and mercileſs <hi>Famine</hi> is entered into our <hi>Gates,</hi> and therefore we cannot but once more aſſay to pierce your eares with our dolefull cries for Iuſtice and Freedom, before your delays wholly conſume the Nation. In particular we earneſtly intreat:</p>
                        <p>Firſt, That ſeeing we conceive this Honorable Houſe is intruſted by the People, with all power to redreſs our grievances, and to provide ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for our Freedoms, by making or repealing Laws, errecting or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhing Courts, diſplacing or plaecing Officers, and the like: And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon this conſideration, we have often made our addreſſes to you, and yet we are made to depend for all our expected good, upon the wils of others who have brought all our miſery <note n="f" place="margin">See the Kings Decla. of the 12 <hi>Aug.</hi> 1642. 1 part book Decla. page 522, 526, 528, 548, &amp; pa. 617.</note> upon us: That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in caſe this Honorable Houſe, wil not, or cannot, according to their truſt, relieve and help us; that it be clearly declared; That we may know to whom, as the <hi>Supream power,</hi> we may make our preſent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116281:16"/>dreſſes before we periſh, or be inforced to flie to the prime Laws of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note n="g" place="margin">See 1 part book decla. pa. 44.150, 382, 466, 637, 699,</note> or refuge.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2.</hi> That as we conceive all Governors and Magistrates, being the ordinance <note n="h" place="margin">See Col. <hi>Nath. Fines</hi> his Speech againſt the Biſhops Canons, made in 164<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>, in a book called Speeches and Paſſages of Parliament, from 3 <hi>Nove.</hi> 1640. to <hi>June</hi> 1641, page 50.51, 52.</note> of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n, before they be the ordinance of God, and no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority being of God, but what is erected by the mutuall conſent of a People: and ſeeing this Honorable Houſe alone repreſents the People of this Nation, that therefore no perſon whatſoever, be permitted to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe any power or Authority in this Nation, who ſhal not clearly and confeſſedly, receive his power from this Houſe, and be always accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the diſcharge of his truſt, to the People in their Repreſenters in Parliament: If otherwiſe, that it be declared who they are which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to themſelves a power according to their own <hi>Wills,</hi> and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as a truſt from the People, that we may know to whoſe <hi>Wils</hi> we must be ſubiect, and under whom we muſt ſuffer ſuch oppreſſions, as they pleaſe, without a poſſibillity of having Iustice againſt them.</p>
                        <p n="3">
                           <hi>3.</hi> That conſidering, that all iuſt Power and Authority in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is not immediatly derived from the People, can be derived only from this Honorable Houſe, and that the People are perpetually ſubiect to Tyranny, when the Iuriſdiction of Courts, and the Power and Authority of Officers are not clearly deſcribed, and their bounds and limits <note n="i" place="margin">See your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance of the ſtate of the kingdom, book decla. pag, 6, 8 See alſo the Acts made this Parliament, that aboliſhed the <hi>Starcham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> and <hi>Hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> Commiſſion.</hi>
                           </note> prefixed; that therefore the Iuriſdiction of every Court or Iudicature, and the Power of every Officer or Miniſter of Iustice, with their bounds and limits, be forthwith declared by this honorable Houſe; and that it be enacted, that the Iudges of every Court, which ſhal exceed its Iuriſdiction, and every other Officer or Miniſter of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which ſhal interm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>dle with matters not coming under his (ogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance, ſhall incurr the forfeiture of his, and their whole eſtates And likewiſe, that all unneceſſary Courts may be forthwith aboliſhed; and that the publike Treaſury, out of which the Officers ſolely ought to be maintained, <note n="k" place="margin">See the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. 1, made 3 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1 <hi>chap.</hi> 26, &amp; 20 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3, 1, and the Judges oath made in the 18 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3, <hi>Anno</hi> 1344, recorded in <hi>Pultons</hi> col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections of ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>tes, <hi>fol.</hi> 144,</note> may be put to the leſſe Charge.</p>
                        <p n="4">
                           <hi>4.</hi> That whereas there are multitudes of Complaints of oppreſſion, by Committees of this Houſe, determining particular matters, which properly appertains to the Cognizance of the ordinary Courts <note n="l" place="margin">See the 29, chap of <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Charta,</hi> and Sir <hi>Ed. Cooks</hi> ezpo ſition upit, in his 2, part <hi>inſtit.</hi> fol. 187, and the Petition of <hi>Right,</hi>
                           </note> of Iuſtice; and whereas many perſons, of faithful and publike ſpirits, have bin, and are dayly moleſted, vexed, Impriſoned by ſuch Committes, ſometimes for not anſwering Interroga ories, and ſometimes for other matters, which are not in Law Criminall; and alſo without any legal
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116281:16"/>warrants expreſſing the cauſe, and commanding the Jaylor ſafely to keep their bodies, untill they be delivered by due courſe <note n="m" place="margin">See the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of right</hi> made in the 3 of the King, &amp; Sir <hi>Edward COOKS</hi> 2 par, <hi>inſti.</hi> fol. 52, 53, 589, 590, 591.</note> of Law; And by theſe oppreſſions, the perſons and eſtates of many are waſted, and deſtroyed: That therefore henceforth, No particular cauſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Criminal or other, which comes under the Cognizance of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Courts of Iuſtice, may be determined by this Houſe, or any Committee thereof, or any other, then by thoſe Courts, whoſe duty it is to execute ſuch Laws as this honorable Houſe ſhal make; and who are to be cenſured by this Houſe in caſe of injuſtice: Always excepted, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters relating to the late War, for Indempnity for your Aſſiſters; and the exact Obſervation of al articles granted to the adverſe <note n="n" place="margin">See <hi>Pſal</hi> 15, 4 See <hi>Rom</hi> 4, 15</note> Party: And that henceforth, no Perſon be moleſted or Impriſoned by the wil or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary powers of any, or for ſuch Matters as are not Crimes, <hi>[o]</hi> according to Law: And that all perſons Impriſoned at preſent for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch matters, or without ſuch legall warrants as aboveſaid, upon what pretence, or by what Authority ſoever, may be forthwith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>least, with due reparations.</p>
                        <p n="5">
                           <hi>5.</hi> That conſidering it s a Badg of our Slavery to a <hi>Norman Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror,</hi> to have our Laws in the French Tongue, and it is little leſſe then brutiſh vaſſalage to be bound to walk by Laws which the People <note n="p" place="margin">See the 36, <hi>Edw.</hi> 3, 15, 80 1 <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>.</hi> 14 7, 11 16, 19, 23 See alſo the Engliſh Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles, in the Raign of Wil. the <hi>Conqueror.</hi>
                           </note> cannot know, that therefore all the Laws and Cuſtoms of this Realm, be immediatly written in our Mothers Tongue <note n="q" place="margin">See <hi>Deut</hi> 30, 12, 13, 14.</note> without any abreviations of words, and the moſt known vulgar hand, <hi>viz.</hi> Roman or Secretary, and that Writs, Proceſſes, and Enroulments, be iſſued forth, entered or inrouled in Engliſh, and ſuch manner of writing as aforeſaid.</p>
                        <p n="6">
                           <hi>6.</hi> That ſeeing in <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which is our Native right, it's pronounced in the name of all Courts, <hi>That we wil ſel to no man, we will not deny, or defer to any man either Juſtice or Right,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding we can obtain no Juſtice or Right, neither from the common ordinary Courts or Judges, nor yet from your own Committees, though it be in caſe of indempnity for ſerving you, without paying a dear price for it; that therefore our native <note n="r" place="margin">See Sir Ed. <hi>Cook</hi> in his 1 part <hi>inſti.</hi> lib. 3 chap 13, Sect, 701, fol, 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>8, where he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares it was the native &amp; ancient Rights of all Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, both by the Statute &amp; Common Law of England, to pay no Fees at all to any Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators of juſtice what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. See al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo 2 part <hi>inſti.</hi> fol, 74, 209, 210, and 176, and he there gives this Reaſon, why Judges ſhould take no fees of any man for doing his office, becauſe he ſhould be free, and at liberty to do juſtice, and not to be fettered with golden fees, as fetters to the ſubvertion or ſuppreſſion of truth and juſtice.</note> Right be reſtored to us, which is now alſo the price of our blood; that in any Court whatſoever, no moneys be extorted from us, under pretence of Fees to the Officers of the Court, or otherwiſe: And that for this end, ſufficient ſallaries or penſions be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116281:17"/>to the Iudges, and Officers of Courts, as <hi>was of old, out of the common Treaſury,</hi> that they may maintain their Clerks and ſervants, and keep their Oaths uprightly; wherein <hi>they ſwear to take no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>y o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Cloaths, or other rewar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>s except meat and drink, in a ſmal quantity, beſides what is allowed them by the King;</hi> and this we may with the more confidence claim as our Right, ſeeing this honorable Houſe hath declared, in caſe of Ship-money, and in the caſe of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Canons that not one peny, by any power whatſoever, could be lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied upon the people, without common conſent in Parliament, and ſure we are that the Fees exacted by Iudges, and Clerks, and Iaylors, and all kind of Miniſters of Iuſtice, are not ſetled upon them by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and therefore by your own declared principles, deſtructive to our property; <note n="ſ" place="margin">See the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of high treaſon in our Chronicles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Iudg <hi>Treſilian,</hi> in <hi>Rich.</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds time.</note> therefore we deſire it may be enacted to be death for any Iudg, Officer, or Minister of Iuſtice, from the higheſt to the loweſt, to exact the leaſt moneys, or the worth of moneys from any perſon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, more then his penſion or ſallary allowed from the Common Treaſury. That no Iudg of any Court may continue above three yeares.</p>
                        <p n="7">
                           <hi>7.</hi> That whereas according to your own complaint in your first Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrance of the <note n="t" place="margin">See 1 part book decla. p. 9.</note> State of the Kingdom, occaſion is given to bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, extortion and partiallity, by reaſon, that judicial places, and other Offices of power and trust, are ſold and bought: That therefore for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of all iniuſtice, it be forthwith enacted, to be death for any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons whatſoever, directly or indirectly, to buy, or ſell, or offer, or receive moneys, or rewards, to procure for themſelves or others, any Office of power or trust whatſoever.</p>
                        <p n="8">
                           <hi>8.</hi> Whereas according to Iustice, and the equitable ſenſe of the Law, Goals and Priſons ought to be only uſed as places of ſafe custody, until the constant appointed time of tryall, and now they are made places of <note n="u" place="margin">See Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Cook</hi> 1 part <hi>Inſti.</hi> lib. 3 Cha. 7. ſect. 438 fol. 260. who expreſly faith, that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment muſt be a ſafe cuſtody, not a puniſhment; and that a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ought to be for keeping men ſafe, not to puniſh them See alſo 2 par. inſtit. fol 589.590.591.</note> torment, and the puniſhment of ſuppoſed offenders, they being detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned many years without any Legal tryalls: That therefore it be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that henceforth no ſuppoſed offender whatſoever, may be denyed his Legal tryall, at the firſt Seſſions, Aſſizes, or Goal delivery, after his Commitment <note n="w" place="margin">See the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the <hi>E.</hi> 3.2. 12 R. 2.10.</note> and that at ſuch tryal, every ſuch ſuppoſed offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der be either condemned or acquitted.</p>
                        <p n="9">
                           <hi>9.</hi> Whereas Monopolies of all kinds have been declared by this honorable Houſe, to be againſt the Fundamentall Laws of the Land, and all ſuch reſtrictions of Trade, do in the conſequence deſtroy not only Liberty but property: That therefore all Monopolies what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116281:17"/>and in particular that oppreſſive Company of Merchant Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers be forthwith aboliſhed, and a free trade reſtored, and that all Monopolizers may give good reparation to the Common-wealth, the particular parties who have been damnified by them, and to be made incapable of bearing any Office of power, or truſt, in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that the Votes of this Houſe <hi>Novemb. 19. 1640.</hi> against their ſiting therein, may be forthwith put in due execution.</p>
                        <p n="10">
                           <hi>10.</hi> Whereas this Houſe hath declared in the firſt Remonſtrance of the <note n="x" place="margin">See 1 part book decl. pa. 14.</note> State of the Kingdom, that Ship-money, and Monopolies, which were impoſed upon the people before the late War, did at leaſt amount to <hi>1400000</hi>
                           <abbr>l.</abbr>
                           <hi>per annum,</hi> and whereas ſince then, the Taxes have been double and treble, and the Army <note n="y" place="margin">See the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation to the Houſe.</note> hath declared that <hi>1300000</hi>
                           <abbr>l.</abbr>
                           <hi>per annum,</hi> would compleatly pay all Forces and Gariſons in the Kingdom, and the Cuſtoms could not but amount to much more then would pay the Navy; ſo that conſidering the vaſt ſums of moneys, raiſed by impoſition of money, the fifth and twentieth part, Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Compoſitions, Exciſe, and otherwiſe, it's conceived much Treaſure is concealed: that therefore an Order iſſue forth immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from this Honorable Houſe, to every Pariſh in the Kingdom, to deliver in without delay to ſome faithful perſons, as perfect an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt as poſſible, of all moneys Leavied in ſuch Town, City, or Pariſh; for what end or uſe ſoever, ſince the begining of the late War, and to return the ſeveral receivers names, and that thoſe who ſhal be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by the ſeveral Pariſhes in every Shire or County, to carry in thoſe accompts to ſome appointed place in the County, may have liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to chooſe the receiver of them, and that thoſe ſelected perſons by the ſeveral Pariſhes in every County or Shire, may have liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to inveſt ſome one faithful perſon in every of their reſpective Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or places, with power to ſit in a Committee at <hi>London</hi> or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, to be the General Accomptants of the Kingdom, who ſhal pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh their Accompts every moneth to the publick view, and that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth there be only one Common Treaſury where the books of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts may be kept by ſeveral perſons, open to the view of all men.</p>
                        <p n="11">
                           <hi>11.</hi> Whereas it hath been the Ancient Liberty of this Nation, that all the Free-born people have freely elected their Repreſenters in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and their Sheriffs and <note n="z" place="margin">28. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1 Chap. 1.8. and 13. See 2 part inſtit. fo. 174.175 where Sir <hi>Ed. Cook</hi> poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively declares that in ancient times by the common law of England, the Coroner, the high She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff, Iuſtices of Peace, Verde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of Foreſts yea and in times of war, the leaders of the Counties ſoldiers, were choſen in ful county by the freeholders.</note> Iustices of the Peace, &amp;c. and that they were abridged of that their native Liberty, by a Statute of the <hi>8. H. 6.7.</hi> That therefore, that Birth-right of all Engliſh men, be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116281:18"/>forthwith reſtored to all which are not, or ſhal not be legally disfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed for ſome criminal cauſe, or are not under <hi>21</hi> years of age, or ſervants, or beggers; and we humbly offer, That every County may have its equal proportion of Repreſenters; and that every County may have its ſeveral diviſions, in which one Repreſenter may be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and that ſome choſen Repreſentatives of every Pariſh proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably may be the Electors of the Sheriffs, Iustices of the Peace, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee-men, Grand-jury men, and all miniſters of Iuſtice Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, in the respective Counties, and that no ſuch miniſter of juſtice may continue in his Office above one whole year, without a new <note n="a" place="margin">It hath been a maxime a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the wiſeſt Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever means to ſettle good Laws, muſt proceed in them with a ſiniſter, or evil opinion of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pole that who ſoever is not wicked, it is for want of opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, &amp; that no State can be wiſely con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fident of any publick mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger then the Rod is over him.</note> Election.</p>
                        <p n="12">
                           <hi>12.</hi> That all Statutes for all kind of Oaths, whether in Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Cities, or other, which inſnare conſcientious people, as alſo other Statutes, injoyning all to hear the Book of Common Prayer, be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with repealed and nulled, and that nothing be impoſed upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of any to compel them to ſin against their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</p>
                        <p n="13">
                           <hi>13.</hi> That the too long continued ſhame of this Nation, <hi>viz.</hi> permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of any to ſuffer ſuch poverty as to beg their bread, may be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with effectually remedied: and to that purpoſe that the Poor be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to chooſe their Truſtees, to diſcover all Stocks, Houſes, Lands, &amp;c. which of right belong to them, and their uſe, that they may ſpeedily receive the benefit thereof; and that ſome good improvement may be made of waſte Grounds for their uſe; and that according to the promiſe of this honorable Houſe, in your firſt Remonſtrance, care be taken forthwith to advance the native commodities of this Nation, that the poor may have better wages for their labor; and that Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures may be increaſed, and the <hi>Herring-fiſhing</hi> upon our own Coaſts may be improved for the beſt advantange of our own Mariners, and the whole Nation.</p>
                        <p n="14">
                           <hi>14.</hi> Whereas that burthenſom Tax of the Exciſe lies heavy only upon the Poorer, and moſt ingenious industrious People, to their intolerable oppreſſion; and that all perſons of large Revenues in Lands, and vaſt eſtates at uſury, bear not the leaſt proportionable weight of that burthen, whereby Trade decays, and all ingenuity and induſtry is diſcouraged: That therefore that oppreſſive way of raiſing money may forthwith ceaſe, and all moneys be raiſed by equal Rates, according to the proportion of mens eſtates.</p>
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:116281:18"/>
                        <p n="15">
                           <hi>15.</hi> That M. <hi>Peter Smart,</hi> Doctor <hi>Leighton,</hi> M. <hi>Ralph Grafton,</hi> M. <hi>Hen. Burton,</hi> Doctor <hi>Baſtwick,</hi> M. <hi>William Prinne,</hi> Lievt. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Iohn Lilburne,</hi> the heires and executors of M. <hi>Brewer,</hi> M. <hi>Iohn Turner,</hi> and all others that ſuffered any cruelty, or falſe illegall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, by the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> the high Commiſſion, or <hi>Councell-Board,</hi> as M. Aederman <hi>Chambers,</hi> and all others that ſuffered oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion before the <hi>Parliament,</hi> for refuſing to pay illegall imposts, customes, or Shipmoney, or yeeld conformity to Monopolizing <hi>Patentees,</hi> may (after <hi>7.</hi> years attendance for juſtice and right) forthwith by this Houſe receive legall and juſt reparations out of the estates of all thoſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, who occaſioned, acted in, or procured their heavy ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, that ſo in future Ages men may not be totally diſcouraged to ſtand for their Liberties and Freedomes, againſt Oppreſſors and Tyrants.</p>
                        <p n="16">
                           <hi>16.</hi> Whereas we can fix our eyes upon no other but this honour able Houſe for reliefe in all theſe our preſſing grievances, untill we ſhall be forced to deſpaire, we therefore deſire, that the most exact care be had of the right constitutions thereof: And therefore we deſire that all Members of this Houſe choſen in their Nonage, may be forthwith e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, and that all Votes for ſuſpenſion of Members from this Houſe may be forthwith put in execution; provided, that the Houſe proceed either finally to expell them, that others may be elected in their ſtead, or they be restored to ſerve their Countrey: And likewiſe that all Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers who are Members of this Houſe (by reaſon of their over-awing power over Judges of their owne making) may wholly attend the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſervice therein, and that every of them may be expelled the Houſe who ſhall hereafter plead any cauſe before any Court or Committee whatſoever, during his Memberſhip in this Houſe: And we further deſire, that every Member of this Houſe may be enjoyned under ſome great penalty, not to be abſent above three dayes, without the expreſſe licenſe of this Houſe, and not above one month without the licence of the place by which they are betruſted: And likewiſe that no Law may be paſſed, unleſſe two third parts of all the Members of this Houſe be preſent, and that the most ſpeedy care be had to distribute Elections equally throughout the Nation.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Now whereas the particular requeſts in our Peritions, are for the moſt part never debated in this Houſe, but when we are at any time rightly interpreted in our meanings and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we onely receive thankes for our good affections, or
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116281:19"/>promiſes that in due time our deſires ſhall be taken into conſideration, and by ſuch delayes our diſtractions are dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increaſed, and our burdens made more heavy; therefore we deſire, that a Committee be forthwith appointed by this honourable Houſe, who may be enjoyned under ſome penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to ſit from day to day, untill they have debated every particular of our requeſts, and reported their ſenſe of the juſtneſſe and neceſſity of them to this Houſe, that we may attend for an anſwer accordingly; and that a time be fixed when ſuch a Committee ſhall make their report. And we further deſire the ſame Committee may be inveſted with power to heare all our other complaints, and offer ſutable remedies to this honourable Houſe, and to bring in the Appeales of any perſons from the Iudges at Weſtminſter, to this honourable Houſe, againſt their injuſtice, bribety, or illegall delay and oppreſſion.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Now O ye worthy Truſtees! let not your eares bee any longer deafe to our importunate cries, let not our deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction be worſe then that of Sodome, who was overthrown in a moment. Let us not pine away with famine and bee worſe then thoſe who die by the ſword. Oh diſſolve not all Government into the prime Lawes of nature, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell us to take the naturall remedy to preſerve our ſelves, which you have declared no people can bee deprived of</hi>
                           <note n="b" place="margin">
                              <hi>See</hi> your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of <hi>May</hi> 19. 1642<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1 book dec. pag. 207. And your Declaration <hi>Nov.</hi> 1642. pa. 728. as alſo pa. 150.</note> 
                           <hi>Oh remember that the righteous God</hi> ſtandeth in the congregation of the mighty, and judgeth among the gods, and ſaith, How <note n="c" place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> long will ye judge unjustly, and accept the perſons of the wicked, defend the poor and fatherleſs, do justice to the afflicted and needy, deliver the poor and needy, and rid them out of the hands of the wicked,</p>
                        <closer>And your Petitioners ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:116281:19"/>
            <p>'TIs indeed called a <hi>Petition,</hi> but the whole frame and matter of it is nothing elſe but a <hi>Calumnie</hi> againſt thoſe they <hi>ſeem to petition,</hi> charging upon their account <hi>all thoſe Evills</hi> that are upon the Kingdome, and a great number more <hi>imaginary ones</hi> which they have <hi>created,</hi> and make men believe they are preſſed with; and publiſh all this to the Kingdome, to render the Parliament <hi>odious</hi> to the People, to <hi>divorce their affections,</hi> and <hi>withdraw their aſsiſtance,</hi> without which, the <hi>Common Enemy</hi> know very well, they are not able to ſettle the peace and tranquillity of the Kingdome from forraigne and domeſtick Force, and <hi>calme</hi> and <hi>compeſce</hi> thoſe <hi>civill and inteſtine aeſtuations,</hi> the remaining diſtempers of our late (almoſt mortall) Diſeaſe, <hi>(of which the motions of the Petitioners are a very conſider a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part)</hi> that thereby a faire way might be paved for a free and equall courſe of Law and Juſtice, (which is a fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meanes to <hi>preſerve peace,</hi> then <hi>reſtore it</hi>) whoſe lower voice cannot be heard while the <hi>Drums beat,</hi> or the <hi>People tumultuate.</hi> It purſues that common and <hi>hatefull Maxime, Calumniate boldly, ſomething will ſtick.</hi> It runs in <hi>generals,</hi> which ever covers <hi>deceipt:</hi> why deſcend you not to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars? The Cries are loud againſt injuſtice, oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, bribery, exacted, extorted Fees, and can you name <hi>no man</hi> that is guilty? You would make all the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you were in an <hi>iron furnace,</hi> and that the Kingdome were an <hi>Hell</hi> to its Inhabitants; and yet tell not who hurts you: But 'tis eaſier to <hi>calumniate</hi> then <hi>accuſe,</hi> and yet to <hi>accuſe,</hi> then to <hi>prove.</hi> Be not abuſed by them that ſerve their deſignes by you; <hi>Accuſe no man falſly,</hi> though upon others informations; look upon the File in which <hi>falſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116281:20"/>accuſers</hi> march, and conſider who may be like to the <hi>Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> A good name is above riches, 'tis ſooner taken away then reſtored: name thoſe Oppreſſors you complaine of, bring forth the <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>the proofe,</hi> and then if you have not juſtice, you may have reaſon to complaine. You com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of <hi>unneceſſary Courts,</hi> and Courts exceeding the <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of their juriſdiction;</hi> you deſire the one to be aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the other to be limited; neither is here <hi>any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar:</hi> Hath not this Parliament taken away the <hi>Starre-Chamber, High Commiſsion,</hi> all the <hi>Biſhops Courts,</hi> the <hi>Court of Wards?</hi> and are not all the <hi>juriſdictions</hi> of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Courts <hi>well knowne?</hi> What have any of the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſuffered by thoſe Courts tranſgreſſing their limits? or what are the <hi>unneceſſary Courts</hi> you meane? was it your <hi>modeſty,</hi> or <hi>want of matter,</hi> that you omit particulars? Untruths are boldly affirmed upon heare-ſay; why are you ſilent in the things that preſſe your ſelves?</p>
            <p>A word or two to your Margent, and then the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the Petition it ſelfe ſhall be a little toucht upon. The Margent you have filled, with Authorities and Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> Statutes, Comments on them, Declarations of &amp;c. Speeches in Parliament; to what purpoſe ſerve theſe? Would you have the Parliament bound in their Parliamentary proceedings by <hi>precedent Lawes?</hi> Were not thoſe Lawes made by Parliament, and is it not the proper work of the Parliament, to <hi>repeale,</hi> as well as to <hi>make</hi> Lawes? Els why doe you deſire in your twelfth Particular, to have the Statutes there mentioned repealed? Either put out your Margent, and deceive not the <hi>ignorant</hi> with a ſhew of that which <hi>ſignifies nothing,</hi> or els reconcile it with your text; unleſſe you meane to ſay, you will appoint the Parliament <hi>what Lawes</hi> they ſhall <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:116281:20"/>and by <hi>what</hi> they ſhall <hi>govern themſelves.</hi> If it be onely to tell them what hath been <hi>done before,</hi> you may take notice, that there are theſe in <hi>that Houſe,</hi> to which you addreſſe, that can as well tell what the Law <hi>new is,</hi> or <hi>heretofore was,</hi> without your <hi>Index,</hi> as they are able to judge what is neceſſary for <hi>the preſent,</hi> or for <hi>the future,</hi> without your <hi>advice</hi> or <hi>intimation.</hi> But you would faine make the People believe, the Parliament neither have <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> enough to know how, nor <hi>fidelity</hi> enough to make them willing to diſcharge their truſt, unleſſe you direct and incite them.</p>
            <p>The Petition is large; to give it an anſwer in <hi>proportion,</hi> were to write a <hi>volume,</hi> which <hi>few</hi> could <hi>buy,</hi> and <hi>fewer</hi> would <hi>read:</hi> and perhaps there is ſomthing of <hi>policy</hi> in the <hi>length,</hi> leaſt their ſeduced numbers ſhould be ſatisfied by a <hi>juſt confutation.</hi> Yet becauſe perhaps there are ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them of <hi>that ſort of people,</hi> to whom <hi>a word is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough;</hi> therefore they may pleaſe to conſider, 'Tis called onely the Petition of <hi>many</hi> Free-borne people of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; 'tis not then, by your own confeſſion, of <hi>all,</hi> or of the <hi>major part:</hi> remember this, and be modeſt for once, act not as if you were <hi>all.</hi> But why many <hi>Free-borne</hi> Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Nation? are there any Engliſhmen that are not <hi>Free-borne?</hi> why doe you diſtinguiſh your ſelves? what need of that <hi>Epithete,</hi> while you addreſſe to the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> who have <hi>aſſerted,</hi> and by the bleſſing of God upon the Councells and Forces of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>vindicated</hi> the <hi>Engliſh Freedome</hi> from the <hi>Common E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy,</hi> under the <hi>ſlavery</hi> of <hi>whom,</hi> by theſe your <hi>dividing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers,</hi> and weake and <hi>out-witted deſignes,</hi> you ſeek to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne,</hi> and carry the <hi>Kingdome</hi> with you.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:116281:21"/>
            <p>To give it the more Authority, the prefacing part of it is forc'd to <hi>ſpeak Scripture;</hi> but not with the <hi>Idiome</hi> of the <hi>Spirit that wrote it,</hi> your <hi>Hebrew</hi> hath much of <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> the breathings of that Spirit are <hi>purity</hi> and <hi>peace;</hi> and the fruits of that Spirit are <hi>love, joy, peace,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You begin with a <hi>ſad complaint,</hi> that the fire of the Lords wrath hath been <hi>among us,</hi> which muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged; and it may be juſtly conceived it is <hi>ſo ſtill;</hi> what meane elſe the diſtempers of the people, that <hi>will not</hi> be healed, and the <hi>actings of diviſion,</hi> together with the <hi>Cries for peace?</hi> But to ſay as you do, that it is <hi>almoſt conſumed,</hi> were <hi>to lie againſt the truth,</hi> and <hi>ſin</hi> againſt <hi>that mercy</hi> which he hath <hi>remembred</hi> in the middeſt of his wrath. This Kingdome hath found the effects of the <hi>rowlings of his bowells,</hi> while it hath been under his <hi>chaſtiſing rod,</hi> that buſh hath <hi>burned,</hi> but 'tis not <hi>conſumed;</hi> and 'tis an <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> that God is in it. 'Tis true, in many places of the Land the <hi>ſcarres of great wounds remaine,</hi> but not as <hi>in Germany;</hi> the lands in England are not <hi>untilled</hi> for want of men, the <hi>thiſtles</hi> grow not in the <hi>furrowes of the field,</hi> the Oxen are yet ſtrong to labour, and the Sheep bring forth their thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands; if you had not intended an <hi>ill uſe</hi> of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, the matter would have borne a <hi>mixture of thanks:</hi> but if ſeems you had rather God ſhould loſe the praiſe of his mercy, then you would omit this Engine, to move the People to murmure and diſcontent.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, that for injuſtice and oppreſſion God hath threatned woes, confuſion and deſolation to any People or Nation; but if your ſearch had been as <hi>due</hi> as you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it was, you might have found other beſides <hi>thoſe,</hi> which you may light upon perhaps, if you would make a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:116281:21"/>
               <hi>review.</hi> It is not to be denied, that oppreſſion and injuſtice cauſe loud cries to heaven, onely remember juſtice is to <hi>render to every one his owne, and not to doe to another what you would not ſhould be done to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>rich</hi> may be <hi>oppreſſed</hi> as well as the <hi>poore,</hi> propriety is to be preſerved <hi>to all:</hi> and a poore man that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the poore, is like a ſweeping raine that leaveth no food.</p>
            <p>You obſerve the <hi>Kings oppreſsions</hi> and how God hath brought him low, and executed fierce wrath upon <hi>his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents.</hi> Why will ye ſuffer your ſelves to be abuſed by <hi>thoſe adherents,</hi> into thoſe <hi>dividing deſtructive</hi> courſes whereby you contribute <hi>directly</hi> to the <hi>reſtoring</hi> of the <hi>Kings</hi> affaires; you are <hi>acted</hi> by his Counſells, and you will not ſee it, and every man ſhall be the Enemy of the people that tels you of it, and if his party ſhall againe get head to the indangering of the Kingdome, which God forbid, thank your owne <hi>petulant importune and unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble interpellations</hi> of <hi>thoſe Councells,</hi> by which through the bleſſing of God, your deliverance had been perfected, if <hi>your ſelves</hi> had not hindred; can you believe the Kings Counſells are changed? or that he wants a party wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an oportunity to bring that upon you which you feare and complaine of? why doe you then give them <hi>hope</hi> and the Parliament <hi>worke,</hi> who have yet ſo much to doe to preſerve the <hi>vitalls</hi> and <hi>recover ſtrength,</hi> that they cannot attend to preſcribe a <hi>topike</hi> to cure the <hi>Morphew on the face?</hi> truſt them with your cure, and allow it <hi>time,</hi> over-haſty ones prove palliate ones, and not ſound. It is the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients part to <hi>declare</hi> his griefe, and <hi>take</hi> his Phyſick, but he muſt let the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> write the <hi>Recipe,</hi> if he deſires the cure ſhould ſucceed.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:116281:22"/>
            <p>That your Petitions were burned, and your ſelves im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned <hi>onely</hi> for petitioning, ſerves to irritate and inrage thoſe whom you have miſled and deceived, a Petition may well deſerve to be burned and the Petitioners puniſhed, if the matter be <hi>unjuſt, falſe, ſcandalous, ſeditious,</hi> read over ſome of your old copies, and ſee if there be none of thoſe faults, 'tis true, it is your <hi>liberty to Petition,</hi> and it is alſo your <hi>duty to acquieſce</hi> in the Parliaments jugement upon it; a Petition is to <hi>ſet forth</hi> your grievances, and not to <hi>give a rule</hi> to the Legiſlative Power, if you meane it ſhall be an <hi>Edict,</hi> which you muſt <hi>compoſe,</hi> and the Parliament muſt <hi>verifie,</hi> call it no more <hi>a Petition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay your Eſtates are expended, how come you then to lay Contributions upon your ſelves for the promoting theſe deſtructive deſignes? is that the way to reimburſe your ſelves? or is it to enable you to fly to the prime laws of nature for refuge? your Margent will teach the Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlative Power to ſuſpect you, and that if you be not <hi>wicked,</hi> it is becauſe perhaps you may not have <hi>oportunity</hi> or <hi>ſtrength</hi> enough, which it will be therefore their care to prevent: and however perhaps it may be true, that theſe ſad troubles have cauſed ſome <hi>diminution</hi> in your Eſtates, yet if you had uſed as much diligence ſince in your owne callings, as you have done in thoſe you <hi>leſſe underſtand,</hi> and had let out the current of your thoughts, which have been miſimployed about <hi>Politiques,</hi> to the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of your families, the account of <hi>loſſe</hi> had not run ſo <hi>high,</hi> and your <hi>private reflections</hi> (if ever you aſſume the trouble of viewing your ſelves) had imbraced you with the ſmiles of a ſweeter peace with him, and your actions <hi>abroad</hi> had leſſe procured the guilt of others.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:116281:22"/>
            <p>Thouſands of families you ſay are improveriſhed, and mercileſſe Famine is entring into your Gates, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore You will once more eſſay to pierce their ears with your dolefull cries for Juſtice and freedome, before the Parliaments delayes conſume the Nation. What <hi>juſtice,</hi> what <hi>freedom</hi> is it you mean<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Which of all the <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars</hi> in your Petition being granted, will be able to turn this <hi>famine</hi> you ſo <hi>aggravate,</hi> into a <hi>plenty?</hi> what an <hi>odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> aſperſion is this, to lay upon the Parliament, to make them hatefull to all men? To tell the World in Print, That there is ſomething in <hi>their power</hi> (for otherwiſe you ſay nothing) that they <hi>delay,</hi> whereby this Dearth and Famine, as you call it, is upon the Kingdom? Have you learned this from thoſe of old? That whenever Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Peſtilence, or any publicker calamity, invaded the World from the juſt hand of God, then to cry out, Throw the Chriſtians to the Lions, attributing to them the cauſe of all, as you do now to the Parliament. Do you not know that the unſeaſonable ſeed-time in 1646. and the unkindly Spring following, might well cauſe a Dearth, which is not yet in <hi>England,</hi> (through the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God) as it is in <hi>other places?</hi> And do you think it is in the power of the Parliament to give a Law to the Heavens, to reſtrain the <hi>Pleiades,</hi> or looſe <hi>Orion,</hi> to <hi>give</hi> or <hi>withhold</hi> rain? can the Parliament make <hi>windows in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> or create a plenty? Why do you ſay you care not what, and abuſe the people without bluſhing?</p>
            <p>Your large Petitory part in 16 Articles, might well receive a very ſhort Anſwer, That it offers many things as <hi>grievances</hi> that are <hi>removed,</hi> deſires many things that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:116281:23"/>are <hi>already</hi> granted, of which you will take no notice, that you may multiply the <hi>Odium,</hi> miſtake the preſent ſtate of things, as if all were an <hi>unformed matter,</hi> or <hi>abraſa tabula</hi> fitted for the <hi>projection</hi> of a <hi>new modell,</hi> or for the compiling of a <hi>new</hi> body of Laws.</p>
            <p>He that will build a City upon a Plain, hath the place <hi>obedient</hi> to his <hi>projections,</hi> and <hi>ſucceptible</hi> of any form; And if he be not prejudiced by <hi>forreign extrinſicall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations,</hi> to which he will conform his lines, he may <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplifie</hi> the beſt Ideas his minde offers him: But he that would reedifie or beautifie an <hi>old one,</hi> will meet with many things that will not ſubmit to <hi>pure technicall</hi> rules; And where it will not, it is not preſently to be <hi>pulled down,</hi> or <hi>ſet on fire. Rome</hi> had a greater beauty and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity as it was built by its firſt Kings, then after the <hi>Burning</hi> by the <hi>Gaules,</hi> and Reſcue by <hi>Camillus,</hi> where each man built as it was moſt Commodious for <hi>him,</hi> and not as it was moſt comely, or convenient for the <hi>whole:</hi> And yet <hi>Catiline</hi> and his Complices were judged <hi>Traytors</hi> for deſigning to <hi>burn it,</hi> and it was <hi>only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Nero</hi> to put it into flames.</p>
            <p>The diſpute is not now of what is <hi>abſolutely beſt</hi> if all were <hi>new,</hi> but of what is <hi>perfectly juſt</hi> as things <hi>now ſtand:</hi> It is not the Parliaments work to ſet up an <hi>Vtopian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth,</hi> or to force the people to <hi>practiſe abſtractions,</hi> but to make them as happy as the <hi>preſent frame</hi> will bear. That wiſe Lawgiver of old, acknowledged that he had not given his people the Laws that were <hi>abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſt,</hi> but the beſt they were <hi>able to receive.</hi> The <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> return of health after ſickneſſe, is to be left to <hi>nature
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116281:23"/>and time;</hi> he that will purge his body, till there remain <hi>nothing peccant,</hi> will ſooner expell <hi>his life,</hi> then the <hi>cauſe of his ſickneſſe.</hi> And he that out of a deſire to repaire his houſe, ſhall move all the foundations, will ſooner be <hi>bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried</hi> in the ruines of the <hi>old,</hi> then <hi>live</hi> to ſee the erection of a <hi>new</hi> ſtructure.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You forget that univerſall rule of Juſtice (to do as you would be doneby) which is not only one of thoſe <hi>con-nate</hi> and <hi>common Notions</hi> which are written in the hearts of <hi>all,</hi> which every one <hi>capable of reaſon,</hi> and <hi>under</hi> wrong, can quote from that <hi>internall writing,</hi> though he that <hi>inferrs</hi> the injury, will not: And it is given alſo as a Compendium of the Law, and an Univerſall rule of Chriſtian Practice, by him who is the <hi>one Lawgiver,</hi> who is able to <hi>ſave</hi> and to <hi>deſtroy;</hi> To whoſe Commands and Dictates, whoever will <hi>profeſs contradiction,</hi> and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue a <hi>contumacious diſobedience,</hi> is more worthy the name of a <hi>Renegado</hi> then a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon forgetfullneſſe of this rule it is, that you would by <hi>force ſpoil</hi> the Lords of their part of the Legiſlative power, which they hold by a claim of an <hi>older date</hi> then any of the Petitioners can ſhew for their <hi>Land:</hi> Ask <hi>your ſelves</hi> the queſtion, Would any of <hi>you</hi> be content to be <hi>diſſeized of his Land,</hi> to which he can derive a title, or <hi>preſcribe to</hi> for ſo long a time? And your contumelious expreſſion of <hi>Patent</hi> Lords might have been ſpared, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Houſes have reſolved that none ſhall be made <hi>Peers of Parliament</hi> hereafter, but by conſent of <hi>both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> whereby your Repreſentors and Truſtees have a Negative voice againſt any ſuch Creation for the future?
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:116281:24"/>Were it not to inlarge this particular beyond what is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the reſt, you might be informed, That there were <hi>Princes</hi> of the people, and <hi>heads</hi> of the Tribes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> and the <hi>f rſt choyce</hi> of them, when they were <hi>new come up</hi> out of Aegypt, and were then <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptive of any form,</hi> was <hi>not</hi> by the people, <hi>but</hi> by <hi>Moſes;</hi> and as it is expreſſe of the Prieſthood, ſo it is evident in the reſt of the Tribes, that the <hi>firſt</hi> of the <hi>firſt line</hi> was ſtill <hi>Prince</hi> of the Tribe.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>longeſt lived, beſt governed, moſt Potent and floriſhing Common-wealths</hi> that ever the <hi>ſun ſaw,</hi> have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes had their Orders of <hi>Nobility</hi> or <hi>Patricians,</hi> in ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion from <hi>Father</hi> to <hi>Son,</hi> preſerved with a <hi>kinde</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in a cleer diſtinction from the <hi>people:</hi> Thoſe two of <hi>Old Rome,</hi> while a <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> And <hi>Venice at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> are <hi>known</hi> Examples. But <hi>this particular</hi> with divers others concerning <hi>Government,</hi> require <hi>a fuller</hi> Tractate then this occaſionall glaunce.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly (beſides their <hi>right</hi>) there is at <hi>leaſt</hi> a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great <hi>conveniency,</hi> if not a <hi>neceſſity,</hi> that the <hi>Legiſlative power</hi> ſhould be in <hi>ſeveral</hi> and <hi>diſtinct bodies</hi> for the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view</hi> of what might elſe be perhaps at firſt <hi>overſeen:</hi> There is ſcarce any man but findes, that reviſing in the <hi>morning</hi> his <hi>evenings conceptions,</hi> he meets with ſomething or other to be <hi>added</hi> or <hi>altered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Are not all <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and all other <hi>Civill Officers,</hi> all <hi>military Officers</hi> both by <hi>ſea</hi> and <hi>land, choſen,</hi> and put into their places, by <hi>both Houſes</hi> of Parliament, wherein, as in <hi>all</hi> other things, the Commons have a <hi>Negative Vote?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:116281:24"/>
            <p n="4">4. Is not there a <hi>Committee</hi> that hath been a good while ſince appointed to receive Informations of <hi>grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances,</hi> and propound them <hi>with remedies</hi> to the <hi>Houſe?</hi> What <hi>addreſſe</hi> have you made to them? Have they <hi>refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> to take your Informations? Why doe you complain <hi>before</hi> you have been refuſed redreſſe?</p>
            <p n="5">5. You complaine of the impriſonment of <hi>faithfull</hi> and <hi>publike</hi> ſpirits, for matters <hi>not criminall,</hi> and would have no impriſonment to be but for crimes, <hi>according to Law.</hi> But are there not ſome actions in theſe <hi>unſetled</hi> times that may <hi>deſerve</hi> a puniſhment, for which no <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> Law hath <hi>explicitely</hi> provided any? You would have no man kept in priſon longer, than till he be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by due courſe of Law. You know there are <hi>two wayes</hi> of delivery by <hi>due</hi> courſe of Law; And he that hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved <hi>the one</hi> ſhould not complaine he is <hi>ſtill</hi> a Priſoner; And for what is a <hi>Crime,</hi> the party <hi>guilty</hi> is no Judge; it cannot be denyed, that as the <hi>Parliament</hi> is the <hi>ſupream Judge,</hi> ſo it is the moſt <hi>competent;</hi> and if they Judge it neceſſary, that <hi>ſeditious Incendiaries</hi> ſhould be <hi>reſtrained,</hi> for the <hi>Peace</hi> of the Kingdome, muſt they give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to the <hi>Delinquents</hi> of the <hi>reaſon</hi> of their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</p>
            <p n="6">6. You would have the Lawes in our <hi>known tongue,</hi> and all writings and proceedings in the preſent <hi>knowne</hi> hands; they have been ſo <hi>heretofore;</hi> What are you now the better for it? Which of you underſtand the <hi>Saxon Lawes,</hi> written in the <hi>then</hi> vulgar tongue? And the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-French, though not then Nationall, yet was <hi>very generally</hi> underſtood. And if moſt of the Petitioners ſhall look upon the language of two or three <hi>Centuries</hi> paſt, they will meet with ſo many words they <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:116281:25"/>not,</hi> as will diſable their underſtanding of the ſenſe of <hi>thoſe they doe.</hi> And if thoſe which are in <hi>other tongues,</hi> were in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> there were a <hi>poſsibility</hi> you might miſtake them, as well as you doe <hi>thoſe</hi> that <hi>already</hi> are ſo. And if there ſhould be a diſuſe in the Courts, of writing thoſe hands which now are <hi>obſolete</hi> to vulgar uſe, the reading of thoſe hands might in time come to be loſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a loſſe of all the Records that are written in them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. If any ſhall <hi>denie</hi> to doe you Juſtice, according to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> unleſſe he may <hi>ſell it,</hi> why doe you not accuſe <hi>the man?</hi> Strike not through <hi>all</hi> by ſuch <hi>oblique in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations,</hi> but let the <hi>guilty</hi> bear his ſhame and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. You might have taken notice, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath <hi>doubled</hi> the ſalaries of the Judges: but to pay all miniſteriall Officers from the <hi>publick Treaſurie,</hi> were to waſte the States treaſure to maintaine the quarrels of <hi>the contentious</hi> againſt them that <hi>are peaceable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. You would have no Judge continue for above <hi>three years;</hi> What ſhall he doe the <hi>reſt</hi> of his life? Were not this to put them upon the <hi>temptation</hi> of the unjuſt Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward? You will ſay he may returne to <hi>private</hi> practice at the Barre againe. Will any of you when he hath <hi>ſet up for himſelf</hi> for the ſpace of <hi>three yeares,</hi> be content to <hi>ſerve journeyman</hi> for the <hi>reſt</hi> of his life? If it be ſo <hi>comely</hi> or <hi>eaſie</hi> a matter, Why did Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lilburn</hi> refuſe the Command of a Troup of Horſe offered him in the Army of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> becauſe he had the title of a Lieutenant Colonel before, And would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of leſſe than a Regiment? Conſider who they are that binde heavie burthens for other men, and grievous to be borne, but themſelves will not touch them with one of their fingers.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:116281:25"/>
            <p n="9">9. For the buying of Offices; ſuppoſe both parties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, yet he muſt have a <hi>large purſe</hi> who can buy of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and 'twill be hard where ſo many muſt be bribed to be ſecret in all.</p>
            <p n="10">10. For that ſpeedy tryall of offenders; your deſire may interferre with Juſtice, matter cannot be alwayes preſently proved, Will you free a man accuſed of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther done the day before the Aſſiſes, becauſe that which hath <hi>vehement preſumptions,</hi> cannot have a <hi>legall Evidence</hi> till ſome dayes after.</p>
            <p n="11">11. The Monopolies you ſo much complain of are condemned by Law, You may take your courſe againſt any, and no man can hinder you. If there be any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolizer in the Houſe, why doe you not declare it to the Houſe, and <hi>prove</hi> it? Have they not formerly put out ſome for that offence? if there be none there, that piece might have been ſpared.</p>
            <p n="12">12. You complain, That the Members of the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> are choſen <hi>onely by Free-holders,</hi> and not by <hi>all</hi> the free-borne people of the Kingdome. If you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it be an Injury to <hi>all</hi> the reſt, that they are <hi>choſen only</hi> by Free-holders, Conſider <hi>ſeriouſly,</hi> and then <hi>tell</hi> Us, whether it be not an <hi>injury to all the reſt,</hi> that they <hi>ſo choſen</hi> muſt be <hi>directed</hi> and <hi>ordered</hi> by <hi>you.</hi> Tell the world how you came by your <hi>Priviledge,</hi> To make a Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſuch as this is, of ſome things <hi>good;</hi> with a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of divers <hi>miſtakes in the reſt,</hi> and then <hi>magiſtically</hi> obtrude it upon the Houſe, <hi>preſently</hi> to paſſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, the <hi>higheſt affront</hi> to the Legiſlative power, and the higheſt <hi>injury</hi> to your free-borne <hi>fellowes</hi> that can be well imagined.</p>
            <p n="13">13. You take notice of the ſhame of the Nation, by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:116281:26"/>the begging of the poor, and it is undeniably a great one, and Peace being ſetled, the remedy of it were one of the moſt <hi>deſirable</hi> things to be undertaken, and this Kingdom wants not materialls for induſtry, and there is not any doubt, that the encouragement of fiſhing in this Kingdome, might produce it a profit of exceeding va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue; but doe You not know that the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath had ſo hard a taske to <hi>preſerve the Land,</hi> that they have had no time left to <hi>improve thoſe advantages of the Sea?</hi> neither can they <hi>give induſtry</hi> to men, which if any will exerciſe in it, they may be ſure of all acceptation. And certainly <hi>that,</hi> and divers <hi>other things</hi> for the good of the Kingdome have been thought upon by the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> (though you would faine have the world believe they mind nothing, unleſſe You be their remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers) and had been in effect <hi>before this time,</hi> had not ſuch conſultations been diverted by the neceſſity of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding againſt <hi>theſe,</hi> and ſome other <hi>diſtempers.</hi> In the meane time, till care can be taken for prevention of <hi>beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery,</hi> increaſe not their <hi>number</hi> by the addition of <hi>your ſelves;</hi> neglect not your Callings, forbear your <hi>clande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Contributions,</hi> You may perhaps thrive in your <hi>own way,</hi> but your unhappy and ill adviſed <hi>Statizing</hi> will ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine your ſelves, and hath a naturall tendency to the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="14">14. You complaine of the heavie burthen of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and there again you pretend to be the <hi>Advocates</hi> of the <hi>poore,</hi> but in nothing are you more the <hi>Kings At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneys,</hi> That ſtanding and conſtant Revenue being that, which of all others with <hi>great eſt eaſe,</hi> ſupplyed the Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies of the Warre when it was <hi>hotteſt,</hi> and contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>moſt</hi> to the breaking of the Enemy. Every thing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:116281:26"/>muſt ſerve to heighten your diſcontent, and to ſtirre up the ignorant people. Otherwiſe tis obvious enough to every <hi>diſcerning eye,</hi> that as tis leaſt grievous of all other wayes, becauſe it paſſeth from a man <hi>unſeen,</hi> ſo it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be <hi>moſt Equall,</hi> becauſe every man is in a ſort his <hi>owne aſſeſſor,</hi> it being in his owne power by his frugallity, to reduce it to as ſmall a ſumme as he pleaſe, the greateſt burthen of it lying upon things <hi>not</hi> neceſſary, <hi>leſſe</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, or, <hi>if</hi> neceſſary, yet there in <hi>ſuch a proportion,</hi> as thoſe which are for the uſe of the <hi>richer</hi> ſort have the <hi>greateſt</hi> impoſition, there being nothing but only ſtrong beer, wherein the <hi>poore</hi> ſeeme to be touched, which for the <hi>too much</hi> abuſe of it, and that even by <hi>the poore,</hi> it may juſtly afford ſomething toward the <hi>maintenance</hi> of the publick, while it is ſo deeply acceſſary to the <hi>undo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of many <hi>private perſons.</hi> For that other, that it is the decay of Trade, and the diſcouragement of all ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and induſtry, You may, if you will but ſend ſome of your <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> into the <hi>united Provinces,</hi> be informed <hi>there,</hi> That that people could never find a foundation of money for thoſe vaſt charges they were forc'd to be at, to defend themſelves from thoſe who tyrannized their Liberties, and to ſettle the free State they have ſince managed, till they had fallen upon the Exciſe; And that notwithſtanding it, their Trade is ſo growne upon them <hi>ſince,</hi> that they have in a great meaſure en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſed it from the reſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> and yet have little matter to raiſe it upon, but their <hi>Induſtrie,</hi> which is not ſo <hi>diſcouraged</hi> by the Exciſe, but it produceth <hi>that effect,</hi> and were worth our <hi>Imitation;</hi> but there was but a word intended, If twere neceſſary, there is nothing more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie than to juſtifie <hi>this way</hi> of Levie <hi>by Exciſe,</hi> before all other wayes whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="15">15. You doe very <hi>magiſterially</hi> appoint the Houſe how
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:116281:27"/>to regulate their Members, and eſpecially thoſe of the <hi>long robe,</hi> who by no meanes may <hi>exerciſe their calling,</hi> becauſe they are called thither to <hi>ſerve the publique;</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gentlemen have their rents and profits come in without their owne particular care, and they who have trades can drive them by their <hi>partners and ſervants,</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe whoſe employments muſt be <hi>perſonall</hi> muſt needs ſuffer <hi>loſſe</hi> in their Eſtates, becauſe they are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. And what reaſon is there why a juſt Judge, who judgeth <hi>according to Law,</hi> and proceeds according to <hi>the rules of the Court,</hi> ſhould be awed by, or afraid of, the perſon of any, though <hi>a Member</hi> of the Houſe? for though <hi>that Houſe</hi> be a <hi>Iudge of the Iudges,</hi> yet the Judge in his Court is Superiour in <hi>that qualification</hi> to <hi>whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever</hi> pleads at his Barre.</p>
            <p>Your <hi>Epilogue</hi> might have been ſpared; the firſt part of it, in regard the Committee You deſire hath been long appointed, to whom any man hath Liberty to bring his grievances, and there is doubt they will be received, and <hi>their ſenſe</hi> of the <hi>juſtneſſe</hi> and <hi>neceſsity</hi> of them be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to the Houſe, though tis probable 'twill not pleaſe <hi>you</hi> concerning <hi>yours,</hi> unleſſe it be <hi>your own ſenſe</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>Your ſecond might be with more Juſtice retorted; Poore <hi>deluded</hi> people! When will yee begin to turne a <hi>deafe Eare</hi> to thoſe who <hi>ſeduce</hi> you? When will you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your <hi>duty,</hi> and come out of your <hi>dreame,</hi> in which you have believed that you are <hi>all the people,</hi> and therefore <hi>ſupreame,</hi> and have arraigned all men in a ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Style? <hi>Act</hi> not a part, <hi>diſſemble not</hi> with Heaven, remember you are in the light and view of <hi>Omniſcience;</hi> Complain not of <hi>Famine</hi> before you <hi>feele it,</hi> leſt you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him that can ſend it. There is a difference between <hi>ſcarcity</hi> and <hi>Famine.</hi> God is the God of order, forbear to endeavour any further to <hi>diſſolve all government</hi> into
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:116281:27"/>Confuſion, leſt you compell the Parliament to prevent it in your <hi>juſt puniſhment;</hi> Remember that God ſtands in your <hi>Clandeſtine Conciliables,</hi> as well as in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Mighty, and as he requires of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates to defend the <hi>poore and needy,</hi> ſo he hath alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to countenance a <hi>poore man</hi> in his cauſe.</p>
            <p>Together with this Petition, there was at the ſame time brought to the Houſe of Commons, by <hi>Colonel Barliſtead,</hi> another <hi>ſcandalous</hi> printed paper, of which two quires had been delivered to one <hi>Lazarus Tindall,</hi> a private ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier of Captaine <hi>Groomes</hi> Company, in the Regiment of the ſaid Colonel, the papers were delivered to him, to ſpread among the ſouldiers of that Regiment, and that ſame perſon that delivered them, told him he ſhould have <hi>one thouſand</hi> of the large Petitions alſo, to diſperſe in <hi>that Regiment,</hi> ſo ſoon as they were reprinted, which they were about to do in a ſmaller leter, for the ſaving of charges. By which it appears that paper alſo ſprings from the ſame root with the foreſaid Petition, of which it alſo takes notice, and helps to promote the ſame ends with it; and who ever ſhall put himſelfe to the trouble to read them both, will finde them ſpeak the <hi>ſame</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and diſcern the <hi>ſame ſpirit</hi> in them both; and is yet more evident by the latter clauſe of the firſt Margi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall note, which were <hi>Lilburns</hi> words to a ſyllable, at the Barre of the Houſe of Commons; And by that para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph of the paper, which begins [have you not upon ſuch pretences] &amp;c. which were <hi>Wildmans</hi> words at that meeting in Well-yard, which is mentioned in Mr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterſons</hi> relation, and at the Commons Barre; and by the laſt clauſe of the next paragraph, which were the words of <hi>Lilburn</hi> and <hi>Wildman,</hi> or one of them, at the Barre of the Houſe of Commons, and are alſo to be found in the Petition it ſelfe, ſo as a very dim ſight may diſcerne it to be <hi>a Whelp</hi> of the ſame <hi>litter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="text">
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:116281:28"/>
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The mournfull Cryes of many thouſand poor Tradeſmen, who are ready to famiſh through decay of Trade.</head>
                        <head type="sub">Or, The warning Tears of the Oppreſſed.</head>
                        <p>OH that the cravings of our Stomacks could be heard by the Parliament and City! Oh that the Tears of our poor famiſhing Babes were botled! Oh that their tender Mothers Cryes for bread to feed them were ingraven in Braſſe! Oh that our pined Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſes were open to every pitifull Eye! Oh that it were known that we ſell our Beds and Cloaths for Bread! Oh our Hearts faint, and we are ready to ſwoon in the top of every Street!</p>
                        <p>O you Members of Parliament, and rich men in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that are at eaſe, and drink Wine in Bowls, and ſtretch your ſelves upon Beds of Down, you that grind our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and flay off our skins, Will no man amonſt you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, will no man behold our faces black with Sorrow and Famine? Is there none to pity? The Sea Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter drawes out the breſt, and gives ſuck to their young ones, and are our Rulers become cruell <hi>like</hi> the Oſtrich in the Wilderneſſe? <hi>Lament.</hi> 4.3.</p>
                        <p>OH ye great men of <hi>England,</hi> will not (think you) the righteous God behold our Affliction, doth not he take notice that you devour us as if our Fleſh were Bread? are not moſt of you either Parliament-men, Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee-men, Cuſtomers, Exciſe-men, Treaſurers, Governors of Towns and Caſtles, or Commanders in the Army, Officers in thoſe Dens of Robbery, the Courts of Law? and are not your Kinſmen and Allies, Colectors of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:116281:28"/>Kings Revenue, or the Biſhops Rents, or Sequeſtratours? What then are your ruffling Silks and Velvets, and your glittering Gold and Silver Laces? are they not the ſweat of our brows, &amp; the wants of our backs &amp; bellies?</p>
                        <p>Its your Taxes, Cuſtoms, and Excize, that compells the Countrey to raiſe the price of food, and to buy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from us but meer abſolute neceſſaries; and then you of the City that buy our Work, muſt have your Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles furniſhed, and your Cups overflow; and therefore will give us little or nothing for our Work, even what you <note n="*" place="margin">And ſince the late Lord Mayor <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> you have put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion art illegall wicked docree of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Councel, whereby you have taken our goods from us if we have gone to the Inns to ſell them to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men; and you have mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered ſome of our poor wives that have gone to Innes to ſinde country men to buy them.</note> pleaſe, becauſe you know we muſt ſell for moneys to ſet our Families on work, or elſe we famiſh: Thus our Fleſh is that whereupon you Rich men live, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you deck and adorn your ſelves. Ye great men, Is it not your plenty and abundance which begets you Pride and Riot? And doth not your Pride beget Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and your Ambition Faction, and your Faction theſe Civil broyles? What elſe but your Ambition and Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on continue our Diſtractions and Oppreſſions? Is not all the Controverſie whoſe <hi>Slaves</hi> the poor ſhall be? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhall be the Kings Vaſſals, or the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or the Independent Factions? And is not the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention nouriſhed, that you whoſe Houſes are full of the ſpoils of your Contrey, might be ſecure from Accounts, while there is nothing but Diſtraction? and that by the tumultuouſneſſe of the people under prodigious oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, you might have fair pretences to keep up an Army, and garriſons? and that under pretence of neceſſity, you may uphold your arbitrary Government by Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>Have you not upon ſuch pretences brought an Army into the bowels of the City? and now Exchange doth riſe already beyond Sea, and no Merchants beyond Sea will truſt their Goods hither, and our own Merchants
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:116281:29"/>conveigh their <note n="*" place="margin">The Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants have already kept back from the Tower, many hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds, and no bulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is brought into the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſo that mony will be more ſcarce daily.</note> Eſtates from hence, ſo there is likely to be no importing of Goods, and then there will be no Exporting, and then our Trade will be utterly loſt, and our Families periſh as it were in a moment.</p>
                        <p>O ye Parliament-men hear our dying cry, <hi>Settle a Peace, ſettle a Peace! ſtrive not who ſhall be greateſt untill you be all confounded.</hi> You may if you will preſently determine where the ſupream Power reſides, and ſettle the juſt common Freedomes of the Nation, ſo that all Parties may equally receive Iuſtice, and injoy their Right, and every one may be as much concerned as other to defend thoſe common Freedoms; you may preſently put down your Arbitrary Committees, and let us be Governed by plain written Lawes, in our own Tongue, and pay your Miniſters of Juſtice out of a common Treaſury, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one may have Juſtice freely and impartially.</p>
                        <p>You have in your hands the Kings, Queens, and Princes Revenue, and Papiſts Lands, and Biſhops, and Deans, and Chapters Lands, and Sequeſtred Lands, at leaſt to the value of eighteen hundred thouſand pounds by the year, Which is at leaſt five hundred thouſand pounds a year more then will pay the Navy, and all the Army, and the Forces which need to be kept up in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and out of that the Kingdoms debts would be paid year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; whereas now you run further into Debt daily, and pay one thouſand pounds by the day at leaſt for uſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Beſides you may if you will Proclaim Liberty, for all to come and diſcover to a Committee of diſingaged men, choſen out of every County, one for a County, to diſcover to them what Monies and Treaſure, your own Members, and your Sequeſtrators, &amp;c. have in their hands, and you may by that means find many Millions of Money to pay the publique Debts. You may find 30000. li. in Mr. <hi>Richard Darley's</hi> hand, 25000. li. in Mr.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:116281:29"/>
                           <hi>Thorpes</hi> hand <note n="*" place="margin">M. <hi>William Lenthall,</hi> Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the Houſe, to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his cozen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, gave 22000 li. to his ſervant Mr. <hi>Cole,</hi> to purchaſe land in his own name, though for his uſe; which he did, and then died ſuddenly, and the land fell to his ſon, and the widdow having marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Lawyer, keeps the land for the childes uſe, and ſaith he knows not that his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor received any mony from the Speaker, and now Mr. Speaker ſueth in Chancery for the land. A hundred ſuch diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries might be made.</note>, a Member of Yours, who firſt Proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> Traytor. And thus you may take off all Taxes preſently, and ſo ſecure Peace, that Trading may revive, and our pining, hungry, famiſhing Families be ſaved.</p>
                        <p>And O ye Souldiers who refuſed to disband, becauſe you would have Iuſtice and Freedom, who cryed till the Earth ecchoed, Iuſtice, Iuſtice; forget not that cry, but cry ſpeedily for Peace and Iuſtice, louder then ever. There is a large Petition of ſome pittifull men, that is now abroad, which contains all our deſires, and were that granted in all things, we ſhould have Trading again, and ſhould not need to beg our Bread, though thoſe men have ſo much mercy, as they would have none to cry in the Streets for Bread.</p>
                        <p>Oh though you be Souldiers, ſhew bowels of Mercy and Pity to a hunger-ſtarved People; Go down to the Parliament, deſire them to conſume and trifle away no more time, but offer your deſires for Us in that large Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, and cry Juſtice, Juſtice; Save, ſave, ſave the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing People; O cry thus till your importunity make them hear you.</p>
                        <p>O Parliament men, and Souldiers! <hi>Neceſsity diſſolves all Laws and Government,</hi> and <hi>Hunger will break through ſtone Walls;</hi> Tender Mothers will ſooner devour You, then the Fruit of their own womb, and Hunger regards no Swords nor Canons. It may be ſo great oppreſſours intend tumults, that they may eſcape in a croud, but your food may then be wanting as well as ours, and your Arms will be hard dyet. O heark, heark at our doors, how our children cry Bread, Bread, Bread; and we now with bleeding hearts, cry once more to you, pity, pity an oppreſſed, inſlaved People: carry our cries in the large Petition to the Parliament, and tell them, if they
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:116281:30"/>be ſtill deaf, the Teares of the oppreſſed will waſh away the foundations of their houſes. Amen, Amen, ſo be it.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>It ſeemes to be written by ſome of the <hi>Profeſſors of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick</hi> in <hi>Newgate,</hi> or <hi>Ludgate,</hi> whoſe long practice of <hi>that kind</hi> of <hi>Oratory</hi> had made him as great a ſtranger to <hi>truth,</hi> as to <hi>bluſhing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> The whole matter of it compoſed of ſo <hi>groſſe</hi> an hypocriſie, that it ſcarce deſerves <hi>that name;</hi> mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>impudency,</hi> and <hi>lyes,</hi> of the ſame <hi>Genius</hi> with the Petition, boldly affirming in <hi>generals,</hi> and brins gnot forth <hi>one particular</hi> with proofe. Where are thoſe <hi>famiſhing babes?</hi> and where are thoſe <hi>pining carkaſſes?</hi> Why are they not brought forth to the view of <hi>ſome</hi> pitifull eye? You cry for <hi>pitie,</hi> why ſhew you not the <hi>object?</hi> Where are thoſe faces <hi>black with ſorrow and famine?</hi> Spend no longer your breath in vaine, Let the famiſhing pined Carkaſſes, thoſe black faces be ſeen, the <hi>view</hi> gives a <hi>deeper impreſsion</hi> then <hi>heare-ſay.</hi> If you be not of thoſe that have ſaid in their hrarts, There is no God, (though your paper abuſe the repetition of that ſacred Name) Remember that the <hi>al-ſeeing God</hi> beholds your hearts, and knowes your <hi>diſtempers, murmurings,</hi> and black <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignations</hi> as well as your <hi>wants,</hi> And ſees with what a <hi>frontleſſe boldneſſe</hi> you affirme any thing, be the untruth never ſo notorious. The language looks more like the <hi>ebullition of wine</hi> than the <hi>cries</hi> of <hi>want.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You complaine of the riſing of the Exchange abroad, that Merchants will not truſt their goods hither, and our Merchants convey their Eſtates. And what is the reaſon thinke you they doe ſo? (if the matter of fact be true) Why <hi>an Army is brought into the bowels of the City.</hi> Doth one Regiment of Horſe, and one of Foot make an Army in your account? And is <hi>White-hall,</hi> and the <hi>Mewes,</hi> in the <hi>bowels</hi> of the City? The Parliament hath had a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:116281:30"/>guard <hi>theſe five yares;</hi> when it was furniſhed from the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and places within the lines, it was held a <hi>great grievance,</hi> And what ſecurity the Parliament had by it was evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent on Monday the 26. of <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt, when either by the <hi>Cowardiſe,</hi> or <hi>Complyance</hi> of the <hi>then guard,</hi> ſo horrid and diſhonourable a violence was put upon the Houſes by an <hi>inconſiderable Rabble</hi> of people. And what <hi>a danger</hi> to trade theſe Regiments are like to be, You might be able to judge, if you would but make an Eſtimate of the <hi>Millions</hi> the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſuffered in, when the <hi>whole Army,</hi> whereof theſe Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are <hi>a part,</hi> marched in Armes through the City, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſixt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> after they had been ſufficiently irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated by ſome of the City: Yet you are not able to bring ſo much as a <hi>loaf of bread</hi> to the <hi>account of loſſe</hi> to the City by all their march, though the ſhops were <hi>open,</hi> and the market <hi>furniſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you would faine uſe any pretence to remove theſe <hi>faithfull forces,</hi> becauſe you ſee as long as they are here, you will hardly be able to make uſe of your <hi>piſtolls and dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> or to <hi>diſſolve all Lawes and Government,</hi> or to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the <hi>prime</hi> Lawes of <hi>Nature.</hi> But indeed twere worth the enquirie, what it is that cauſes this great export<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Eſtates, and that hinders all importation, 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a diſeaſe that muſt needs <hi>deſtroy,</hi> though not in a <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> There hath been a good while a rumour of <hi>a peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> that walketh in <hi>darkneſſe;</hi> and hath been known to have <hi>infected ſome</hi> that frequent <hi>your meetings,</hi> and are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as your <hi>own;</hi> and this rumour is not a <hi>whiſpering,</hi> it hath ſpoken almoſt as loud as ſome of your <hi>Cries for bread,</hi> And 'tis the Doctrine of <hi>Parity</hi> or <hi>levelling,</hi> bringing all mens Eſtates to an <hi>Equallity;</hi> A <hi>notion</hi> that <hi>Merchants,</hi> and men of <hi>great Trade,</hi> are as little <hi>edified</hi> with, as either <hi>the Lords</hi> are with being <hi>deveſted</hi> of their <hi>Honours,</hi> and <hi>part</hi> in the <hi>Legiſlative power,</hi> or other Gentlemen to part with
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:116281:31"/>their <hi>Lands,</hi> and therefore having ſo good meanes to put them <hi>out of your reach,</hi> which other men <hi>have not,</hi> may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps tranſport them, not willing their large <hi>perſonall</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates ſhould come under your <hi>Diſtribution,</hi> from which there an be <hi>no recovery.</hi> And if you thinke that Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize be <hi>good</hi> for the Kingdome, and if you have any care of <hi>that</hi> good, you muſt conſider how to ſatisfie Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, that you intend <hi>not to levell;</hi> for their Trade runs <hi>ſuch an hazzard,</hi> and muſt be managed with <hi>ſuch a diligence,</hi> and <hi>induſtry,</hi> as will hardly receive <hi>incouragement</hi> from your <hi>Vtopian parity.</hi> And however the Croud of thoſe that follow you intend no ſuch thing, but thinke theſe are wayes to ſecure their own property; yet <hi>juſt ſuſpition</hi> is upon <hi>many of you,</hi> And tis not your <hi>bare deniall</hi> will ſerve, good words will not ſatisfie. You know who ſaid <hi>Hayle Maſter,</hi> when the <hi>ſalutation</hi> was a <hi>watchword.</hi> It might be thought there would be nothing of greater <hi>deferency</hi> and <hi>reſpect,</hi> than the <hi>addreſſe of your Petition</hi> in the <hi>ſuperlative inſcription,</hi> yet <hi>Lilburn</hi> told you at the meeting in <hi>VVell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard,</hi> that when you had once <hi>raiſed the ſpirits of the pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> you would then <hi>force the Houſe</hi> to grant what you ask. Confide not in <hi>your preſent intentions,</hi> remember <hi>Hazael.</hi> There is not the <hi>moſt clear and Candid ſoule amongſt you</hi> that knowes to what (now abhorred) actions he may be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the <hi>violence</hi> of the people, if <hi>that Sea</hi> ſhall once <hi>break over his bankes,</hi> and twill not be then in <hi>their power</hi> to ſtop, but only is <hi>his</hi> that <hi>calmeth the Sea and rebuketh the raging of the people,</hi> who can ſay <hi>to both, hitherto ſhalt thou come and no further, and here ſhall thy proud waves be ſtayed.</hi> But to paſſe by all the reſt, be perſwaded to examine the truth of fact with a little more care when you compoſe your next <hi>ſeditious Harangue;</hi> You may take notice, how ill your intelligence hath been in <hi>this;</hi> It's poſſible indeed, much of the publique money may be in Collectors, Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:116281:31"/>and ſequeſtrators hands, and it were a <hi>meritorious ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> to the Common-wealth to <hi>diſcover it,</hi> and would no doubt be of <hi>univerſall acceptance;</hi> but be ſure you be right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inform'd, <hi>accuſe no man falſly,</hi> ſpecially in <hi>print,</hi> 'tis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Charity, to which Grace no Chriſtian ſhould be a ſtranger. Bring the particulars and proofes to the Houſe, that a courſe may be taken to bring that money in to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the neceſſities of the Common-wealth, which are great; ſome paines taken to the purpoſe in <hi>this ſervice,</hi> will be more worth than <hi>all your Petitioning.</hi> But for theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars here produced, they are ſo farre from <hi>truth,</hi> as makes your whole paper ſuſpected to proceed from the <hi>Father of lyes.</hi> You ſay there is 25000. <abbr>l.</abbr> in Mr. <hi>Thorps</hi> hands, a Member of the Houſe of Commons. He was never appointed or authoriſed Treaſurer, or Collector of any publique moneys, either by the Parliament, or any Committee, or any others, nor ever received <hi>one penny</hi> of the publique moneys. Mr. <hi>Richard Darley</hi> was indeed appointed to receive ſome moneys in the Eaſt riding of <hi>Yorkeſhier,</hi> But he never received more himſelfe than ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty three pound or therabouts, which was upon occaſion of calling the Sequeſtrators of <hi>Beverly</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; At which time his Deputy receiver, Mr. <hi>Richard Thornton,</hi> being not there, he received it himſelfe, and put it to account. All other moneys were received by his ſaid Deputy, who hath from time to time paid out the ſame, according to ſuch Orders as he received for that purpoſe. Mr. <hi>Darley</hi> knowes not particularly what is at preſent in his Deputies hand, in regard he is here at <hi>London,</hi> attending his ſervice in the Houſe of Commons, and his Deputy is in <hi>Yorkeſhier,</hi> neither yet can he tell whether he may not have already accounted with the Committee of the County; how ever he knowes it cannot be any great ſumme, and the account for the whole is ready, when
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:116281:32"/>it ſhall be called for; And ſo is alſo the money remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when Order ſhall be given for it. But your famous miſtake, is that of your <hi>margent</hi> concerning Mr. Speaker, The truth of which ſtory <hi>upon through inquiry,</hi> inſtead of what you have Printed, is clearly <hi>thus,</hi> That Mr. <hi>William Lenthall</hi> Speaker of the Houſe of Commons, <hi>never purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Land,</hi> either in his <hi>own,</hi> or any <hi>other mans name</hi> ſince <hi>theſe troubles;</hi> neither did Mr. <hi>Cole purchaſe any</hi> for him; Mr. <hi>Cole</hi> died not ſuddenly, but of a <hi>Fever,</hi> and that after <hi>ten or twelve days ſicknes;</hi> his wife is ſtill a widdow, and not married either to <hi>Lawyer,</hi> or <hi>any other;</hi> there is <hi>no ſute</hi> againſt her by Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> nor <hi>cauſe of any.</hi> You ſay an hundred ſuch diſcoveries might be made as this latter, and indeed its true, they may be done with <hi>great eaſe,</hi> it is but to ſit down and write an hundred particulars <hi>what comes upermoſt,</hi> taking only care there be <hi>never a true word in them,</hi> which the <hi>ſuggeſtor of this</hi> will eaſily <hi>enable</hi> you to do, and then there will be an hundred ſuch <hi>diſcoveries</hi> made; but indeed he that would take paines to examine both your Petition, and this Paper, and had ſo little to do with precious time, as ſo to imploy it, might finde among your <hi>Complaints, Suggeſtions,</hi> &amp; <hi>Calculations,</hi> ſome <hi>convenient number</hi> of truths of the <hi>ſame Complexion</hi> with <hi>theſe:</hi> But as you may know the <hi>Lion</hi> by his <hi>claw,</hi> ſo you may know the <hi>Devill</hi> by his <hi>tongue,</hi> he is a <hi>liar, and the Father of lies;</hi> and certainly this your <hi>miſtaken confidence</hi> may be ſufficient to <hi>command belief</hi> from ſuch as are <hi>content</hi> to be deceived in <hi>all your Generals,</hi> for information in <hi>which,</hi> it is not credible you would take more <hi>care,</hi> then in <hi>theſe</hi> particulars, which both concerned the reputation of <hi>particular Gentlemen,</hi> and whereof the truth might be <hi>inquired out.</hi> But now how will you do theſe Gentlemen <hi>right</hi> in this, and give them <hi>reparations?</hi> perhaps your <hi>ſcandalous Paper,</hi> by the great diligence of <hi>your ſelves,</hi> and <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> to ſpread them, may come to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:116281:32"/>many hands where their <hi>juſt</hi> defence may not follow, and perhaps they may eſcape more <hi>proper uſes,</hi> ſo as to remain when the Gentlemen ſhall be <hi>at reſt,</hi> and be a <hi>black Epitaph</hi> upon their <hi>innocency,</hi> and an <hi>unjuſt</hi> and <hi>unworthy Blot</hi> upon their <hi>fair reputation.</hi> If any man ſhall after this be miſled by theſe guides, it will not be an eaſie matter to undeceive him, but he is to be Pitied, as one of thoſe who being <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len out</hi> with <hi>truth,</hi> is given up to <hi>ſtrong deluſions</hi> to beleeve <hi>a lye.</hi> Be yet adviſed not to <hi>feign a</hi> neceſſity, and hold out that as a Vail to <hi>your Reſolution to diſſolve all Laws of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> it may confound propriety, and levell Eſtates, the thing perhaps that ſome aime at: But it may cauſe a <hi>promiſcuous mingling of blood too,</hi> and in ſuch a confuſion as you <hi>ſeek to introduce,</hi> it is not impoſſible you may <hi>loſe your own</hi> in the <hi>Croud.</hi> Call not <hi>up</hi> therefore more ſpirits then you know how to conjure <hi>down,</hi> yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Spels may <hi>fail</hi> you, there may be ſome have <hi>Piſtols</hi> and <hi>Daggers,</hi> that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>care for your Spels</hi> nor <hi>you,</hi> nor <hi>your Petition neither.</hi> While you <hi>plot</hi> tragedies, and indeavor thus to <hi>bring</hi> them upon the <hi>Stage,</hi> take heed there <hi>enter not ſome</hi> who will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take their <hi>Cu</hi> from your <hi>Prompter,</hi> nor <hi>Act</hi> according to your <hi>Poets deſign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhall adde noe further trouble to the Reader, and indeed very much of this might have been ſpared, as to thoſe who have their parts exerciſed to diſcern good and evill. The evill of this is ſo written, that they that <hi>run</hi> might <hi>read it,</hi> if prejudice did not <hi>blinde them,</hi> if perhaps there be not alſo ſome that <hi>do not ſee,</hi> becauſe they <hi>will not ſee;</hi> but becauſe there are ſome, who in the <hi>ſimplicity</hi> of their hearts, have followed thoſe <hi>Impoſtors,</hi> let them ſuffer themſelves to make <hi>halt</hi> in this <hi>furious march,</hi> and a little to conſider their <hi>leader,</hi> and then think <hi>whither</hi> they are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; let them take a meaſure of <hi>Lilburn</hi> by his books filled <hi>with falſhoods and bitterneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> by his <hi>ingratitude</hi> to thoſe <hi>who
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:116281:33"/>have obliged him,</hi> by that behaviour in the Houſe of Lords, that <hi>wants a name;</hi> by the <hi>Piſtoll and Dagger</hi> he ſpeaks of, by which <hi>murder was deſigned,</hi> which he cals a <hi>noble reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution;</hi> by his company, the moſt deſperate Malignants; by their opinion of him, as being wholly the Kings; by all theſe Actions which tend to <hi>ſtir up</hi> the people, to <hi>force the power</hi> which your Petition acknowledgeth <hi>ſupream,</hi> and thereby to <hi>diſſolve all Government, and mingle all with ruine;</hi> then judge <hi>impartially,</hi> if this be the <hi>Character</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> or a <hi>Banditto;</hi> of a man acted and guided by the Spirit of God, or moved and driven by the Devill: And think if it be <hi>becoming</hi> men profeſſing Religion to be found in <hi>theſe wayes.</hi> To be Religious is no more in <hi>deſpiſing forms</hi> then in <hi>adoring them,</hi> The power of it is in <hi>Conforming the will of man to the will of God,</hi> and in all the <hi>goings out of that will</hi> either into <hi>affection,</hi> or <hi>action,</hi> with an <hi>unreſerved reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> to give up the man to be guided ſtill, by the <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall rule of truth and gooddeſſe,</hi> of which there is <hi>ſufficient,</hi> and <hi>cleerely enough</hi> laid down in the word of truth, for direction in all things to him that <hi>humbly ſeeks it</hi> of which You ſhould have made <hi>more uſe</hi> in <hi>ſincerity</hi> and <hi>humility</hi> to <hi>direct your ſelves,</hi> and <hi>leſſe</hi> in <hi>prevaricating</hi> and <hi>miſapplying</hi> it with a ſpirit of bitterneſſe, to make it ſerve for the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage in which you would <hi>falſly accuſe,</hi> not your <hi>brethren,</hi> but your <hi>confeſſed Superiours.</hi> Be perſwaded to <hi>ſtudy to be quiet, and doe your owne buſineſſe,</hi> to <hi>live in peace, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you;</hi> and leave the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique affaires to <hi>thoſe,</hi> to whom <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Kingdome</hi> hath <hi>committed them;</hi> abuſe not <hi>lenity,</hi> but make uſe of thus much for your faire <hi>retreat,</hi> and <hi>charge no more;</hi> nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake <hi>any further</hi> to <hi>prastiſe</hi> till you be a great deale bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>ſtudied in,</hi> and have more <hi>univerſall, comprehenſion of,</hi> that very <hi>important,</hi> and yet <hi>very little known art</hi> of <hi>Statizing.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
